Leader Nui?
Leader Nui?
Yen Jiang will
Yen Jianghui
with this
with this
speech
speech
is
er
please, China
please, China
It's fourteen
是十四享業
once a month for the first time in 2014
每個月一次是2014年的第一次
But it's the last time in twelve years
但是是十二年的最後一次
Because next year will be a new year
因為馬上明年就是小年月
Say hello to everyone
跟大家拜個二年
I am very pleased to invite Dr. Chen Jindi from the Institute of Chemistry today
今天很高興請到化學所的陳錦蒂博士
To introduce this colorful world
來介紹這個彩色的世界
from the traditional rash
從傳統的染疹
Optoelectronic technology from craftsmanship to fashion
工藝到時尚的光電科技
Then Dr. Chen is now in the Institute of Chemistry
那陳博士是現在化學所的
The main areas of the researcher are
研究員主要的領域是
Organic Optoelectronic Materials
有機光電材料
Including Organic Light Emitting Diodes
包括有機發光二級體
and research and development of organic solar cell materials
以及有機太陽能電池材料的研發
Tamkang University
大學是在淡江大學
In 1982, he joined the Department of Chemistry, National Taiwan University.
1982年到台大化學系
I got a master's degree in my laboratory
我的實驗室拿了碩士
Then he got military service
然後扶了兵役
Then went to America in 1987
然後在1987年去美國
the University of Illinois
那個伊利諾大學
Received Ph.D. in 1992
在1992年拿到博士
Then at Caltech
然後在加州理工學院
Three years as a postdoctoral fellow
做了三年的博士後
Joined the Institute of Chemistry in 1995
95年就加入化學所的行列
Then when everyone is a postdoctoral fellow
然後大家在博士後的時候
Ph.D. and postdoctoral
就開始博士跟博士後
non-linear optical materials
都研究非線性光學材料
This thing is following the light
這個東西就是跟在有見光
Visible light is strongly absorbed
可見光有強烈吸收有關
After returning to Taiwan in 1995
那從95年回到台灣以後
The initial research topic was organic light-emitting diodes
開始的研究課題就是有機發光二級體
Organic light-emitting diodes are now many
有機發光二級體就是現在很多
These very colorful materials inside a flat-panel display
平面顯示器裡頭這些很彩色繽紛的材料
The electrons emit light and then emit various kinds of light
電子發光然後發各種不同的光
Then in the last five or six years, we have been researching solar cell materials
然後最近五六年都研究太陽能電池材料
Then you know if you want to absorb solar energy
那你知道要吸收太陽能的話
That is, all kinds of attractive materials
也就是各種吸引的材料
Can absorb sunlight very effectively
能夠很有效的吸收太陽光
So there are some materials related to the color
所以都是跟顏色有關的一些材料
is its specialty
就是它的專長
So the topic of its speech today is this colorful world
所以它今天的演講題目就是這個彩色世界
That Dr. Chen can in 2002
那陳博士能在2002年
Awarded the third Tsinghua Chemical Science, Technology, Culture and Education Foundation
獲頒第三屆的清華化學科技文教基金會的
outstanding period
傑出期
In 2003, he won the Research Works Award for Young Scholars from Academia Sinica
2003年獲得中央研究院的青年學者研究著作獎
In 2004, won the case award of patent and transfer of Academia Sinica in that year
2004年獲得該年度中研院專利及計轉的個案獎勵
Therefore, there are more than 100 papers, more than ten patents, and three special books
所以論文超過百篇專利超過十項有三個專書
It is for him to serve as the deputy director of the Institute of Chemistry from 2005 to 2009
是讓他2005年到2009年也服務化學所擔任副所長
So this subject and even his research specialty
所以這個題目甚至他研究的專長
So we welcome Dr. Chen to talk about designing the world with warm applause
所以我們以熱烈的掌聲來歡迎陳博士來講採設世界
Thank you, Peng Fude, for introducing
好謝謝彭富德介紹
In fact he was my teacher
事實上他是我的老師
He should be called Mr. Peng respectfully.
應該尊稱他一聲彭老師才對的
Now because everyone is working since graduation
現在因為在自從畢業之後大家都在工作了
So now it is considered to be serving in the same unit
所以現在變成算是在同個單位服務
have this chance
有這個機會
This was also successfully invited by Mr. Peng.
這個也成功彭老師的邀請了
Come and make one for everyone before Chinese New Year
在過年前來給大家做一個
Such a report of a feast of knowledge
這樣子的一個知識饗宴的報告
because of the new year
因為過年的關係
so i think
所以我想
The topic I think is also very suitable for this season
我想的題目也非常符合這個時節
Here are some colorful ones for you
就為大家獻上一些色彩繽紛的
beautiful pattern
漂亮的圖案
After seeing it like this
這樣子看了之後
Everyone can go back to celebrate the New Year happily
大家能夠高高興興地回去過年
This is a question of comparing penises
這個比較陰莖的一個題目了
Okay, this topic is
好 這個題目就是
Mainly talking about dyes
主要在講染料的部分
Dyes I think everyone knows very well
染料我想大家非常清楚
Everyone knows that since childhood
從小學到現在大家都知道說
This is the part about color
這個是有關於色彩的部分
In fact, this color
那這個色彩事實上
I want to talk about the origin of some history
是要講一些歷史的由來
This is what you see
各位手上看到的這個
inside the disaster of the speech
演講的災要裡面
mentioned this
就有提到這個
I'll tell you a little bit about the discovery of this color in a moment.
等一下我就會講一段這個色彩發現的
The origin of history
歷史的由來啦
sorry
對不起
This laser ratio is somewhat
這個雷射比有點
good this
好這個
talk about color
要講色彩
In fact, I want to explain a little bit about the origin of this color
事實上要跟大家稍微說明一下這個色彩的由來
The reason why there are colors on the earth
地球上之所以會有色彩
Generates a relationship between the sun and the sun
產生完全之間的太陽的關係
The basis for this is very simple
這個根據很簡單的這個
In fact this happens this color
事實上這個發生這個色彩
One of them is a very famous person
其中有一個是很有名的一個人
It's Newton
就是牛頓
what about this experiment
這個實驗呢
The experiment in a forest environment called Newton
這位叫做牛頓的一個山林境的實驗
because you all know
因為各位都知道
If you put the sunlight in this mountain forest
這個山林境如果你把太陽光
shine on the forest
照在山林境上
It can decompose the sunlight into various colors
它就可以把這個太陽光分解開成各式各樣的顏色
Let's talk about this colorful neon color
我們講說這個七彩霓虹的顏色
red orange yellow green blue green purple
紅澄黃綠藍綠紫
So in fact sunlight is
所以事實上太陽光是
Sources of colors that our human eyes see all over the planet
整個地球上我們人眼睛看得到色彩的來源
from the sun
就是來自於太陽光
what color
這個顏色呢
Add all colors of red, orange, yellow, green, blue, green and purple together
紅澄黃綠藍綠紫全部顏色加在一起
becomes white
就變成了白色的
so we see sunlight
所以我們看到太陽光
Predominantly white light color
主要是白色的光色
Of course this algae turns yellow
當然這個藻成黃黃的顏色
will be a bit off
會有點偏差
Algae turned yellow will be closer to yellow-orange color
藻成黃黃的會比較偏近黃橘色的顏色
Among Japanese people, the light color is closer to pure white
日人當中是比較偏近純白色的光色
This is because the atmosphere is dry and old sunlight
這個是因為大氣乾老的太陽光
According to the color of the earth, there are some distorted colors
照著到地球這個色彩有一些折色
produced by the phenomenon of color twisting
繞色的現象所產生的
Humans have five senses
人的有五官
Inside the facial features of a person
人的五官裡面
In fact, only the eyes are responsible for seeing
事實上就只有眼睛在負責看東西
Seeing things is that our human eyes are able to distinguish
看東西是我們人的眼睛是能夠區分出
Different colors of light come out
不同的顏色的光色的出來的
Because of the structural relationship between our eyes and people
因為我們眼睛人的構造關係所造成的
This is the reason for the origin of a simple color
這個就是簡單的一個色彩的由來的原因
This visible light sun actually emits a lot
這個可見光太陽事實上會發出很多
The radiant energy of different bands comes out
不同波段的輻射能量出來
Visible light from the sun can only
可見光太陽只能夠
It's just the visible light in a short area
只是其中一個短短的一個區域裡面的可見光
What about all the sources of radiation?
整個所有的輻射的光源呢
is very widely distributed
是分佈的範圍非常的廣泛
from what everyone knows
從大家知道的聽到的
The ones on the radio are called radio waves
收音機的這個叫做無線電波
That is a type of energy emitted by sunlight
那個都屬於太陽光會發射出來的能量的一種
Or let's talk about a kind of light wave
或者我們講說光波的一種
Visible light is only in this wide band
可見光只是在這個這麼寬廣的波段裡面
within a narrow range
很窄的一個範圍之內
What is the shortest possible X-ray and cosmic color line?
最短的可以到什麼X光、宇宙色線
It is one of the rays emitted by the sun
都屬於太陽會發射出來的光線之一
The fact that our human eyes see the color of objects
我們人眼睛看到物件的顏色的事實上
This is about color
這個要講到色彩學的
mainly due to two or three factors
主要是有兩三種的因素所造成的
We'll actually get to that shortly later
我們後面事實上馬上就會提到
This basic color is caused by two reasons
這個基本上色彩是有兩種原因造成
one is additive color
一個是加成性的色彩
a color called vanishing
一個叫做消去型的色彩
let's look at this first
我們先看這個
This is not an analysis from another angle
這不是從另外一個角度來做分析說
what color is this
這個顏色是怎麼
our human eyes
我們人眼睛
see what color is made of
看到顏色是什麼構成的
Burning hot paper of full red lip aperture like sun light
太陽光之類的全部紅唇光圈的燃熱紙
If your stuff is transparent
如果你的東西是透明的話
All light will pass through
所有的光射就全部都會穿透過去
None of the beams will be blocked
沒有任何一個光射會被阻擋下來
In this example it means
這個例子裡面就是說
It shoots light except red and orange
它把除了紅跟橘的光射
let it penetrate outside
讓它穿透之外
Everything else will be absorbed
其他的都會吸收下來之後
Then what we see with our eyes is
這時候我們所眼睛看到的就是
light passing through
能夠穿透過去的光射
In the example drawn above the figure
在這個圖上面畫的這個例子裡面
This is what our eyes see
就是我們眼睛看到的就是這個東西
it's red orange
就是紅橘色
In the middle example
在中間這個例子裡面
It allows the blue and sky blue to pass through
它就讓藍色跟天藍色會穿透過去
At this time, the object we saw
這時候我們看到的這個物件
it's sky blue
就是天藍色的東西
by analogy
一使類推
This thing looks yellow-green
這個東西看起來就是黃綠色
Because this yellow-green light can pass through
因為這種黃綠色的光可以穿透過去
So what our eyes see
所以我們眼睛看到的東西
In fact one of the sun's rays
事實上是太陽光的一個
We call it Complementary Color
我們稱之為叫做護補色
In addition to penetrating
這個護補的現象除了穿透
cause this phenomenon to occur
造成這個現象的發生
another one is
還有一個就是
The principle of reflection is the same, resulting in the same effect
反射的原理也是一樣造成同樣的效果
If you don't have a thing that will be absorbed by your object
你如果沒有一個東西會被你的物件吸收的話
then you see all the rays
那你就看到所有的光射
See all the principles of red and yellow
紅色、黃色的原理全部都看到
then what you see is white light
那你就看到的是白光
same
同樣的
If all your other lights except red and orange
如果你所有的其他光射除了紅的、橘的
no absorption
沒有吸收之外
The red and orange will be reflected by it
那紅的橘的就會被它反射出來
At this time, what you see will also be red.
這時候你看到的東西也就會是紅色
This is explained by the phenomenon of reflection
這是利用反射的現象來解釋說
The color the object renders
物件呈現的顏色
It is to make it adhere to the same principle as when penetrating
是讓它所秉持的原理就跟穿透的時候一樣
something not absorbed by that thing
沒有被那個東西吸收掉的東西
and be seen by our eyes
而被我們眼睛看到
That's where the colors we see come from
那個就是我們所看到的顏色的由來
this is from
這個是從
So what our eyes see is the color of the object
所以我們眼睛看到的是物體的顏色
In fact, it is the protection shot of the light shot
事實上是光射的護補射
Our Chen's tail is called Hubushe
我們陳的尾叫做護補射
is caused by this reason
是因為這個原因造成的
This shield shot causes the color of many objects
這個護補射造成很多物件的顏色
A very important reason for the color of objects
造成物件顏色的一個很主要的原因
what we see most
我們最常看到的
Ink sprayed over a watch
噴過一表機的墨水
you go buy this ink cartridge
你去買這個墨水夾
There will be these three dots on it
上面就會有這個三個點
this color ink cartridge
這個彩色墨水夾
It's going to have this cyan, magenta, and yellow dotted on it.
裡面會點上了這個青色、洋紅色跟黃色
What about these three colors?
這三個顏色呢
It's actually on this color chart
事實上是在這個色表圖上面
It's actually the three colors on this side
它事實上是在這個邊邊的三個顏色
The three colors of Y, M, and C
Y、M、C的這三個顏色
What about these three colors?
那這三個顏色呢
In fact like yellow
事實上譬如說像黃色
Actually the complementary color of blue
事實上是藍色的互補色
What about the cyan color?
那這個青色呢
it is the complementary color of red
它是紅色的互補色
Then the color of sheep's head red is the complementary color of green
那這個羊頭紅的顏色是綠色的互補色
The red, blue, green
那紅的、藍的、綠的
we call it tricolor
我們稱之為叫做三顏色
What about the three colors?
這個三顏色呢
after being absorbed
被吸收掉之後
you'll see its complementary color
你就會看到它的互補色
It is the three colors of Y, M and C we just talked about
就是我們剛剛講的這個Y、M、C這三個顏色
In fact we can see that
事實上我們可以看到是
so-called complementary colors
就是所謂的互補色
caused this removal
造成這個卸下
that paint
那那個油漆啊
Will melt, color, this paint and so on
會化、色彩、這個塗料這些東西
all are
全都是
Wujie you because I just saw it before
物界你因為剛剛前面我看過
it is not absorbed by it
它沒有被它吸收
The color after being worn by us
被我們穿後的顏色
and it reflects
還有就是它反射出來
colors not absorbed by it
沒有被它吸收的顏色
The origin of the complementary colors we see
我們所看到的互補色是這麼的由來
In fact, on light compensation
在光補上面事實上
You can do progressive analysis like
你可以做進步的分析就是
If you absorb the color of this area
如果你吸收掉的是這個區域的顏色
Just now this area was red and orange
剛才這個區域是紅道橘
a little yellow in color
有一點黃色的顏色
If the color in this area is absorbed
如果這個區域的顏色被吸收掉
all your eyes can see
你眼睛所能夠看到就只剩下
Green Natural Blue
綠色 天然色 藍色
This is called complementary relationship
這個叫做互補的關係
So there are three cases
所以有三種情形
What we say in terms of triadic colors
我們用三元色來講的話
There are three situations
就有這三種情形
This is the second case
這是第二種情形
put the yellow green blue thin tone in the middle
把中間的黃色 綠色 藍色 細色調
Your eyes can only see red and blue around it
你眼睛只能看到紅色跟邊邊的藍色
The third is that you put the short wavelength
第三個就是你把短波長的
This fine shade of blue green natural color
這個藍的 綠的 天然色的細色調
Your eyes can only see long wavelengths
你眼睛只能看到長波長的
yellow and red
黃的跟紅的
This is the reason for the complementary color of the object
這個是物件出現互補色的原因
That's right, that's how it's explained by industry scholars.
是這麼 事產學讓是這麼來解釋的
Of course if you absorb all the light colors
當然如果你把所有的光色都吸收掉
what color is that
那是什麼顏色呢
It becomes black in the middle
就變成中間的黑色了
you can't see anything
你什麼東西都看不到
because all the light is absorbed by the object
因為所有的光線都被物件給吸收掉
so you can't see any color
所以你任何顏色都看不到
Can't see any color is black
任何顏色都看不到就是黑色
So black is also a color
所以黑色也算是一種顏色
The color with nothing is called black
就是什麼東西都沒有的顏色就叫做黑色
Alright, this next has to do with chemistry comparisons
好,這個接下來要跟化學比較有關係
This is because I am doing chemistry
這個因為我是化學做化學的
We say that these colors come from sunlight
那這些顏色我們講說是從太陽光來的
But in fact matter
但是事實上物質呢
Our place to see is matter
我們的地方看到是物質
The substance itself will produce some color
這個物質本身會有一些顏色的產生
These colors arise entirely from the
這些顏色的產生完全是由於
caused by the basic chemical elements of which a substance is composed
所構成物質的基本化學元素所造成的
then listen to all matter
那這個聽一下所有的物質
We roughly divide into two categories
我們大致上分成兩大類
called organic materials or inorganic substances
叫做有機材料或者是無機的物質
How to distinguish between organic and inorganic
有機無機的區分方式
this is in chemistry
這個在化學裡面
We usually use this to distinguish
我們通常是用這樣來區分
If you have a lot of
如果你的節目裡面還有很多
The elements carbon, hydrogen, oxygen, nitrogen
碳、氫、氧、氮這些元素的話
this is called organic matter
這叫做有機物質
like us
譬如說像我們
The amino acids we eat, the vitamin
我們吃的胺基酸這個維生素
Or the sugar we eat, these are made into organic matter
或者是我們吃的糖這些都是要做有機物質
And the fat we eat is still there
還有我們吃的油脂這些都還是有
Swallow these elemental things of green oxygen egg
吞青氧蛋的這些元素的東西
This stuff is called organic matter
這種東西叫做有機物質
In addition to these few I use black circles
除了這幾個我有用黑色的圈圈
outside of the circled elements
圈起來的這些元素之外
The periodic table has more than 100 images in total
周期表像總共有100多
100 now has 10 to 110 more elements
100現在有10到110多個元素
Deduct these elements
扣掉這幾個元素之外
substances made of other elements
其他的元素所構成的物質
Inorganic matter
總統統都叫做無機的物質
This substance is divided into two categories
這個物質就分成這兩道類
The color is also composed of these materials
那構成色彩也是由這些材料所構成的
organic and inorganic
分成有機跟無機
But the reasons for the colors they produce are different
但是他們所產的色彩的理由不太一樣
This is a substance made up of inorganic elements
這個是由無機的元素所構成的物質
the colors it makes
它構成的色彩
actually depends on the size of your composing elements
事實上取決於你的構成的元素的大小
Like this Buddha these are
像這個佛這些都是
Lu Shu's substance
魯樹的物質
Buddha is gas
佛是氣體
it itself is yellow
它本身是黃色
slightly yellow
略帶黃色
slightly bigger green
綠稍微大一點
that is green
那個是帶綠色
show is liquid
秀是液體的
but it's orange
但是它是帶的是橘紅色
then click
然後點呢
turns purple
就變成紫色
it's bigger
它更大
The color will vary with the size of this atom
顏色會隨著這個原子的大小
different means i change
不同的意思是我改變
Another class is made of these metals
另外一類是由這些金屬的
made up of ions or elements
離子或是元素所構成的
Different ions have different colors
不同的離子它具有不同的顏色
For example, like this tire
譬如說像這個胎
In fact, white has no color
事實上是白色沒有顏色的
what about this one
這個個呢
or fall?
或是落呢
is yellow
是黃色的
Its color has something to do with its structure
它這個顏色又跟它的結構又有一些關係
For example, these two are called Falling Frost and Ion
譬如說這兩個都是叫做落霜跟離子
It's just that this is a two sticks connected together
只是這個是一個兩把連在一起
But this structure is different
但是這個結構不一樣
Its constituent metal elements are the same
它構成的金屬元素是相同的
But the structurally different relationship
但是結構不同的關係
cause different colors
造成顏色不一樣
These are a characteristic of inorganic materials
這些是無機材料的一個特徵
its color big
它的顏色的大
What's the depth
的深淺呢
or different colors
或是不同的色彩呢
depends on the size of the atom
取決於原子的大小
or its structure
或是它的結構
to make an impact
來造成影響
This is an inorganic material
這是無機材料
Organic materials as I just said
有機材料就我剛講過
The whole medium is composed of elements in carbon, oxygen and nitrogen
全中是由碳天氧氮中原素所構成的
its color composition
它的色彩構成呢
In fact, with these carbon-carbon doubles
事實上要靠著這些碳碳雙件
If there is no carbon-carbon double piece
沒有碳碳雙件的話
all organic matter
這些所有的有機物質
usually no color
通常都是沒有顏色
is transparent
就是透明的
The shade of this color is
這個顏色的深淺的就是
Red, blue, green?
是紅的藍的綠的呢
Depends on the amount of this carbon-carbon double
取決於這個碳碳雙件的多寡
Let's talk about this carbon-carbon double piece
這個碳碳雙件我們講說
it has beat electrons
它是具有拍電子
beat more electrons
拍電子越多
your color will be darker
你的色彩就會越深
The color will be longer wavelength
會顏色就會越往長波長
It is the direction of the red offset
就是紅的那方向偏移
it may have been blue at first
剛開始的時候可能是藍色
later turned green
後來是變成綠色
may be yellow
可能是黃色
Then there is orange red
再來是橘色 紅色
The longer the wavelength of the color
顏色的波長越長呢
So I beat the number of electrons more and more
所以我隨著拍電子的數目越多
while there is a proportional increase
而有成比例的增加
as organic and inorganic compounds
作為有機化物跟無機化物的
The color produced is actually not the same principle
產生的顏色事實上原理是不太一樣的
But the result is the same
但是結果一樣就是
Causes the appearance of colors in visible light
造成了可見光的顏色的出現
Our eyes can perceive this visible light
我們眼睛可以感受到這個可見光
So people are the reason why they can see colors
所以人的是可以看得到色彩的原因
Although different substances
雖然是不同的物質
the principle is the same
原理是相同的一樣的
Let me give you an example soon
這個我很快舉個例子給大家看
Like the ones pictured here
像這邊畫的這幾個
all organic matter
都是有機物質
And these substances actually have different colors
而這些物質事實上有不同的顏色的
for example this
譬如說這個
This looks like the shortest molecule
這個看起來就是分子最短的一個
its absorbing wavelength
它的吸收的波長
It's actually the shortest of the four.
事實上也是在這四個裡面最短的一個
its absorption wavelength
它的吸收波長
The location is probably in this place
位置大概是落在這個地方
It absorbs blue light
它把藍色的光都給吸收掉了
So our eyes see this
所以我們眼睛看到這樣子的
Substances that absorb blue light
會吸收藍色光的物質
In fact, it will appear more or less yellowish
事實上會呈現出大概偏黃色的
color appears
顏色出現
This one is slightly longer
這個稍微分子長一點
Take more electrons
拍電子多了一些
Its absorption wavelength will be slightly longer
它的吸收波長就會稍微長一點
It absorbs mainly green light
它吸收的主要是綠色的光線
Complementary colors that our eyes see
我們眼睛所看到的互補色
is to show a color like this carambola
就是呈現出像這個陽桃紅的顏色
monodentate pile
這個一齒類堆
If it continues to grow
再繼續長下去的話
Its absorption wavelength becomes more and more to the right
它的吸收波長就越來越往右邊
Go ahead, this side absorbs the yellow-orange color
前進 這邊是吸收了黃橘色的
The color it presents at this time
這時候它所呈現出來的顏色
It will be the color of the complementary color below, Iron Blue
就會下面這個互補色的顏色 鐵藍色
And finally if it hides to a certain extent
然後最後它如果藏到一個程度
it absorbs red light
它會吸收紅色的光線
At this time, the substance will show a green luster.
這時候物質會呈現出綠色的光澤出來
This is exactly a rendering of a complementary color
這個是完全是一個互補色的一個呈現
Okay, this is about the color
好 這個講到這個色彩
I'm starting to tell the history of this color discovery
我開始要講這個色彩發現的歷史了
In this so-called chemical technology
在這個所謂的化學這個技術
or before technology
或者科技出現之前
Human beings can get colors from nature
人類能夠拿到色彩就是取之於大自然
I saw this here and found a few photos for everyone to see.
這邊有看到這個找了幾張照片給大家看
The most primitive and primitive bibliophile
最原始最原始的查書師
It's always written in the book
書上都會這麼寫的
The source of the most original color is taken from nature
最原始的顏色的來源是取之於大自然
For example, this ingredient
譬如說這個食材
This is called sporite
這個叫做刺鐵岩
It's the color that produces that orange-red color
它是產生那個橘紅色的顏色
There is another one called Zheshi
還有一個叫做者石
this translated word
這個翻譯字
This color is a stone showing this dark purple color
這個顏色是呈現出這個暗紫紅色的顏色的石頭
so you can see this stone age
所以你可以看到這個石器時代
The colors painted on the walls of this cave
畫在這個洞壁上面的顏色
last saved until now
最後保存到現在
Why do you still see the pattern caused by these two colors?
怎麼還看到的就是這兩種顏色造成的圖案
Because at that time it was possible to obtain colors from nature
因為那時候能夠取得於大自然的顏色
Probably the most common are these two colors
大概最常見的就是這兩種顏色
so you look at this mural
所以你看這個壁畫
Most of them are renderings of these two colors
大部分都是呈現出這兩種顏色的呈現
Then this is all things from the stone age
那這個都是石器時代的所有東西
After the emergence of human culture
開始有人類文化出現之後
marl culture like ingal
像印加爾的馬爾文化
Or China's ice cat swimming that painted
或是中國這個冰貓泳那個彩繪
The color painted on the artist's face
藝人臉上塗的這個色彩
with egypt
跟埃及
Egypt is one of these major civilizations
埃及算是這個幾大股文明的其中一個
You can see the color it takes inside
你可以看到它裡面所采取的顏色
Most of them are biased towards this orange
大部分都是偏向於這個橘紅色
or this pleated red color
或是這種褶紅色這種顏色
because at that time
因為那時候
The source of the most accessible colors
最容易獲得的顏色的來源
is the material from these colors
就是來自於這些顏色的材料
while the color material itself provides the most
而顏色的材料本身提供最多的
these two colors
就是這兩種顏色
you go to the book
這個你去查書
the book will tell you
書上會告訴你說
this ever
這個有史以來
the first human way
第一個用人類的方式
synthetic artificial coloring
合成出來的人工的色素
It's in this pharaoh's tomb
就是在這個法老王古墓裡面
see this blue substance
看到這個藍色的物質
Because this blue substance does not exist in nature
因為這個藍色的物質在自然界不存在的
It is artificially synthesized
它是經過人工的合成
Only then can this blue pigment appear
才能夠獲得這個藍色的這個色素出現
Here we use the current chemical technology
這邊我們以現在的化學的技術來講
The ancient Egyptian
當初這個古埃及人
How did they go about creating this color?
他們是怎麼樣子去把這個顏色給創造出來呢
or did he mix it up with three things
還是他用了三種東西把它混在一起
processed by Galle
經過加勒的處理
will be able to generate this thing
就能夠產生這個東西
This thing is called Acidic Copper Tears
這部東西叫做細酸帶銅的眼淚
Although it is something like a stone
雖然是類似像石頭的東西
But this stone is colored
但是這個石頭是有顏色的
The color is the natural color
顏色就是天然色這個顏色
what are these three things it uses
它用的這三個東西是什麼
The main source of color is from this
主要的顏色來源是來自於這個
Copper Carbonate
銅的碳酸眼淚化物
This thing is called malachite
這個東西叫做孔雀石
this is in
這個在
presumably earlier
想必在比較早的時候
Egypt has a lot of this malachite
埃及有很多這種孔雀石
So they can get local material
所以他們就可以就地取材
Use this as the source of the color
用這個來當作顏色的來源
The colors they make are natural colors
他們做的顏色是天然色
Then the quartz sand mixed in
然後裡面混的石英沙
Quartz sand is the Sally by the sea
石英沙就是海邊的那個沙利
main source
主要的來源
that egypt in
那埃及在
Where
在哪裡
In North Africa there is a large
在北非有一個很大的
salad desert
沙拉沙漠
There are many quartz stones in the salad desert
沙拉沙漠裡面多的是石英石
So this material is not a problem
所以這個取材也不是個問題
Then there's the marble
再來就是大理石
is the source of carbonated limestone
就是碳酸蓋石灰石的來源
There are many such things in the world of Egypt
埃及世上也有很多這樣的東西
mixing these three things together
把這三個東西混在一起
Originally malachite was this greenish thing
本來孔雀石是這個偏綠色的東西
After the result is processed like this
結果這樣處理之後
it becomes natural color
它就變成天然色
This is the record you can find
這個是你可以查到的記錄
That's the first artificial
就是這是第一個人工
artificially synthesized
用人工合成出來
but it is derived from the infinite substance
的射速 但是它是取之於無極的物質
There are no such things as carbon, hydrogen, oxygen and nitrogen in it.
裡面並沒有還有碳氫氧氮這些東西
So it's the rate of fire of the infinite dye
所以它這是無極的染料的射速
Well, those colors, of course this was discovered a long time ago
好 那個這些色彩當然這個很早以前發現了
Then it was later used in the creation of this art
然後後來就用在這個藝術的創作上面
I found a few pictures that can be found on the Internet
我找了幾張網路上可以找得到的圖片
For example, the last supper of Jesus
譬如說這個耶穌最後的晚餐這個上面
I’ve been to this place before, which city in Italy doesn’t matter
這個地方我還去過 這個義大利的不要哪個城市
Teacher Peng took us there
那時候是彭老師帶我們去的
This one is actually a colored lake
這個上面事實上是一個彩色的湖會
"Monalis" is smiling, look at the fact
《摩納利斯》在微笑 你看這個事實上
The color has faded over time.
因為時間很久的關係 顏色都退掉了
It fades into the color of that yellow coffee color
就退成那個黃色咖啡色的這種顏色
In fact, it turned out to be a colored substance
事實上原來是彩色的物質
These are famous paintings
這個都是很有名的畫
colorful colors on top
上面都色彩繽紛的顏色
Including the more modern ones like this Monet
包括像這個墨內比較近代一點的
But it is also a painting more than a hundred years ago
不過也是一百多年前的畫
This is also his painting, this one is called
這個是也是他的畫 這個叫做
"In Spring Mountain" I can't find out what is the name of this
《春山裡》這個我找不出來這個名字叫什麼
used in these things
這些東西裡面都用到了
These pigment dyes
這些色素染料
But because of the relationship at that time
但是因為那時候的關係
Because this is an earlier relationship
因為這比較早期的關係
Relationships over a hundred years ago
一百多年前的關係
At that time there was no synthesis technology
那時候還沒有合成的技術出現
In fact, they are all raw materials
都要事實上都是取材無積的材料
e.g. white pigment
譬如說白色的色素
At that time, it was made of carbon fiber, sulfate fiber
那時候是由碳酸纖、硫酸纖
made of oxidized fiber
跟氧化纖所構成的
The yellow one is made of this acid fiber
黃色的是由這個落酸纖
The blue one is made of this
藍色的是由這個
This iron complex is composed of
這個鐵的錯核物所構成的
Composed of elements such as red blood fiber and yellow blood fiber
赤血纖、黃血纖這些元素所構成的
Green is ash
綠色就是落酸纖
Composition of yellow blood fiber, red blood fiber and acid copper
交代到黃血纖、赤血纖跟出酸銅所構成
This is all information you can find on the Internet.
這個都是網路上你可以查得到的資料
The red color is composed of the fibrous compounds of wood acid and
紅色是由這個木酸跟的纖的化物所構成的
And these oxide fibers and copper oxide
還有這些氧化纖跟氧化銅所構成的
These are the early paintings
這個是早期的那些繪畫
Just use these non-productive pigment dyes
就是用這些無積的色素染料
to do drawing work
來做繪圖的工作
The fact that these product-free materials are also used in
這些無積的材料的事實上也是用在
The things used in this printing into the newspaper
在這個印刷融入報紙裡面所用到的東西
This is holding up to now to compare
這個牽著到現在比較
Civilization above the printed work we do
文明上面我們做的印刷的工作
Most of the oil used for release
釋放用的大部分的油末
All come from the materials composed of these inorganic substances
都是來自於這些無機物質所構成的材料
it will come in a variety of different colors
它會有各式各樣不同的顏色出現
The setting of the inorganic pigment like this
這個這樣子無機的顏料的設置
It is also used in this yellow line of the gang line
也用在這個幫馬線的這個黃色的線上
The reason why I mention this is
我之所以的話提這呢是
It turns out that the yellow line is mainly made of these
原來這個黃色線主要都是由這些
made of inorganic compounds
無機化物所構成的
like this vulcanized septum or
像這個硫化隔或者是
Acid drop this kind of thing
落酸籤這種東西
This thing we just saw earlier
我們剛剛前面看到過的這個東西
But it's really on the pavement now
但是呢是它現在真正鋪帶馬路上
There's a lot of these yellow paints too
也有很多這些黃色的塗料呢
made of organic matter
是由有機物質所構成的
There is an English text here
這個這邊有一篇英文的文字
I took it from this website
我是從這個網站上摘錄下來的
This site says
這個網站它就講說
Wall-making-Pent Composition
Wall-making-Pent Composition
The road style of these yellow board horse lines
這些黃色板馬線的道路風格
the end of its oil
線的它的油末
what is the composition of the paint
油漆的成分是什麼
This is explaining the composition of these paints
這個在解釋說這些油漆的成分
Usually made of this fluidized terrier or Lutheran
通常都是由這個流化梗或路德西的構成
But now there are a lot of yellow poultices like this
但是現在有很多這樣子的黃色的塗藥
is made of this thing
是由這個東西所構成的
This thing is called Benzidine Yellow
這個東西叫做Benzidine Yellow
Translated into this text is called Lianben Anhuang
翻成這個文叫做聯本安皇
This is made of an organic substance
這個就是一個有機的物質所構成的
substance with a yellow color
有黃色顏色的物質
what about this thing
這個東西呢
Because there are some chemicals
因為是有些化物了
The release of this same thing is also used in many current cars.
同樣這個東西釋放也用在很多現在的汽車的
paint on car body
車殼的塗料上面
For example, the yellow color of the little yellow we are talking about
譬如說我們講的小黃的那個黃色
It's actually made of this yellow paint substance
事實上就是由這個黃色的油漆物質所構成
And the substance of this paint is actually
而這個油漆的物質事實上
Made entirely of organic matter
完全是由有機的物質所構成的
you will see it has many
你會看到它有很多
Pai Tan Tan double key Pai electronic
拍探探雙鍵 拍電子
There are a lot of rings on this one
好多個本環這個上面
So many rings connected together
那麼多個本環連在一起
it will appear in color
它就會有顏色的出現
depends on your chemical structure
就看你的化學結構
This is all organic matter
這個全都是有機的物質
like this one is showing this fuchsia
像這個呢是呈現出這個紫紅色
This one is showing this bright red color
這個呢就是呈現出這個鮮紅色
This should be an Alfa Romeo sports car
這個應該是阿法羅密歐的跑車
This red grilled chicken above
上面這個紅色的烤雞
Only use organic substances
只讓用的是有機的物質當中
its color rendering
它的色彩的呈現
And what about this dark blue substance?
然後這個深藍色的物質呢
by this car
是由這輛車子呢
is made of this dye
是由這個染料所構成的
Finally there is a bright green
最後還有一個鮮綠色
this is very colorful
這個很鮮艷
like the color of this ninja turtle
像這個忍者龜的顏色
This is made up of the molecules of this macrocycle
這個是由這個大環的分子所構成的
These are the organic substances that came out later
這些就是後來才出來的有機物質
Usually the color of organic matter
通常有機物質的顏色呢
Will be brighter and brighter than the color of inorganic substances
會比無機物質的顏色色彩的鮮艷亮麗
because its color is the intensity of the sunlight it absorbs
因為它的色彩是吸收太陽光的強度
is relatively strong
是比較強的
So what about Rong Gong's bone-protecting color?
所以容共呈現出來的護骨色呢
will be stronger
也會比較強烈
This is how it looks compared to the inorganic material
跟那個無機的材料比起來是這個樣子
So what about organic matter?
所以有機的物質呢
One advantage of having this is
有這個一個優勢就是
Because it is more colorful
因為它的色彩比較艷麗
So everyone prefers to color like this
所以大家比較喜歡把這樣子色彩
showy things add to us
艷麗的東西加在我們
in our daily use
我們日常的使用的東西裡面
Because the colors that appear in this way
因為這樣子所呈現出來的色彩
will be brighter and brighter
會更鮮豔更亮麗
Our race likes to look at that beautiful thing
我們人種是喜歡看那個很漂亮的東西
strong color
色彩很強烈
It means very beautiful
就是代表很漂亮的意思
Including this of our female compatriots
包括這個我們這個女性同胞
Facial makeup also includes the use of various paints
臉部的化妝也是包括用了各式各樣的塗料
Because there are all kinds of colors
因為各種顏色都有
In the early days, put these paints like this
早期那時放這些塗料就是像這個
Like painting, it contains these heavy metals
繪畫一樣裡面都是含有這些重金屬
Everyone knows that metals are not very healthy for the human body.
各位都知道中金屬對人體不是很健康的一個東西
So now these cosmetics
所以現在這些化妝品裡面
It has largely discarded these heavy metal-containing paints
它大致上都已經捨棄的這些含有重金屬的塗料
Instead, organic substances are used as the color ingredients in cosmetics.
而改成用有機的物質來當作化妝品裡面的顏色的成分了
Well, this is me talking about modern times in one breath, right?
好這個是我一下一口氣就講到現代了對不對
But you have to think about it
可是你要回想一下就是說
These things are all because of chemical synthesis
這些東西都是因為化學的合成
These various organic substances are produced
產生了這些各式各樣的有機的物質
Organic matter is in fact basically
有機的物質事實上基本上是
The colors of these organic substances seen now
現在看到的這些有機物質的顏色
Of course it was synthesized in the laboratory.
當然就是實驗室裡面合成出來的
or synthesized by the industry
或是工業界合成出來的
Early organic matter was also
早期的有機物質也是有
But we can see it but we can't use it
但是我們看得到但是卻用不到
Because these early organic substances were roughly drawn from
因為這些早期的這些有機物質都取材大致來
For example, flowers show very bright colors
譬如說花卉就呈現出非常艷麗的顏色
What about the colors in the flowers?
花卉裡面的顏色呢
are also composed of these organic substances
也都是由這些有機物質所構成的
But whether these substances are the color of flowers
但是這些物質不管是花卉的顏色
or the color inside an animal's feathers
或者是動物的羽毛裡面的顏色
you can find a way to extract it
你可以想辦法把它萃取出來
But these substances are not stable enough
但是這些物質都穩定度都不是很夠
Not long after you worked so hard to extract it
你辛辛苦苦把它萃取出來之後沒多久
their color fades
它們顏色就退掉了
So early these brightly colored substances
所以早期的這些顏色鮮豔的物質
It took a lot of effort to get
都是要獲得花了很大的功夫
I went to find a piece of information here.
我這邊去查到一筆資料就是
It was the early days, which should have been in the Middle Ages.
就是早期這個應該是中古世紀的時候的
flowers of the color of that time
那時候的顏色的花
It is still difficult to obtain
獲得的仍然還是很困難
At that time, there was a color called Taizi's dye
那時候有一種顏色是叫做太兒子的染料
This Taizi is translated from the English name
這個太兒子是從英文的名稱翻譯過來的
How did this dye get it?
這個染料它是怎麼獲得的呢?
I learn a lot of English writing here
我這邊學人多英文寫的
Let me translate for you
我幫各位翻譯一下
It's near the Mediterranean Sea and there's a man called Flying Mudbot
是地中海的附近有個叫做飛泥機人
The Mudbots live next to the Mediterranean Sea
飛泥機人是住在地中海的旁邊上面
There is a type of crustacean in that region of the Mediterranean Sea
地中海那個區域有一類的那個甲殼魚
This is what the crustacean inside it looks like
它這個裡面甲殼魚長的是這個樣子
You can find photos on the Internet
你可以找得到網路上的照片
There is something in this color
這個裡面含有一種顏色的東西
When you extract it, it takes on this purple color
你把它萃取出來是呈現出這種紫色的顏色
So in the middle ages
所以在那個中古世紀的時候
to get this color
為了獲得這個顏色
Because what was the color actually used for later?
因為這個顏色事實上後來被用在什麼?
That this is the Pope's holy robe
那個這個是教宗的這個聖袍上面
You see this is a very famous portrait of Christianity
你看這個是基督教的一個很有名的一個畫像
the angel inside
裡面這個天使啊
this is still
這還是
jesus doesn't know what
耶穌還不曉得是什麼
The robe it wears is the prince
它裡面穿的那個袍子就是這個太兒子
The color dyed by this dye
這個染料所染上去的顏色
But the dye didn’t exist at that time, and the chemical solution didn’t come out yet.
但是這個染料那時候沒有那個化工液還沒有出來
How does this person synthesize these organic dyes?
這個人還剝小的怎麼去合成這些有機的染料
It's from this crustacean to extract it
它是從這個甲殼魚去把它提煉出來的
Here's a narrative I'm talking about
這邊有一個敘述我講說
you want to dye a dress like this
你要染一件這樣的衣服
do you know how many shells this crustacean needs
你知道需要多少殼這個甲殼魚嗎
He said he wanted 10,000,000,100,000,12,000 of these crustaceans
他說要各十百千萬一萬兩千顆這個甲殼魚
To be able to dye this piece of clothing
才能夠染這個一段這個衣服而已
So you can know how difficult it is to obtain this pigment
所以可以知道這個顏料的獲得有多麼的困難
So at that time in the Middle Ages
所以在那個時候中古世紀的時候
Pigments are very, very difficult to obtain
顏料的獲得非常的非常的困難
So if you can have a color like this color
所以如果你能夠擁有這個這樣子顏色的色彩
Usually a symbol of some kind of power
通常都是一個什麼權貴的象徵
Those who are not expensive can afford it
非貴給付的人才能夠買得起
can afford this color
用得起這樣子的顏色
this is
這個是
is a history that you can look up
是一個你可以查得到的這個歷史
Before artificially synthesizing these dyes
在用人為的方式合成這些染料之前
Acquiring dyes is quite a difficult thing
染料的獲取是相當的困難的一件事情
We often hear people say
我們常常聽人講說
What kind of tree roots are you going to extract from?
就要從什麼樹根萃取出來
This has a ready-made example
這個有一個現成的例子
This is called fenugreek root
這個叫做芡草根
What color is the root of the chickweed
芡草根的顏色是那種
brick red color
磚紅色的顏色
Because there is one like this in it
因為它裡面還有這樣子的一個
The substance of the organic dye appears
有機的染料的物質出現
So you use the extraction method
所以你用萃取的方法
from a tree root like this
可以從這樣子的樹根裡面
Extract the substance of such a color
提煉出這樣子的顏色的物質出來
so you can know
所以你可以知道
The color is not fetched from
顏色獲取不是從
All cancel a natural world
都是取消一隻大自然界的
like canceling a fake shellfish
像是取消一個假殼魚類
Otherwise, this is extracted from the root of the tree.
不然這個就是從樹根裡面提煉出來
it's a hard job
是很辛苦的一件事情
The current situation like this
這個這樣子的現況
Until about 100 years ago
一直到大概100多年前
Of course the one 150 years ago
當然150年前的這位
We now call him the emergence of Chemist
我們現在稱之為他叫化工師傅的出現
This situation has taken a big turn
這情況有了一個很大的轉
We now respectfully call it chemical production
我們現在尊稱它為化工製作
it's british called william burkey
它是英國人叫做威廉伯基
It existed from 1838 to 1907
它存在的年代是1838年到1907年
Probably around the end of the last century to the beginning of the last century
大概是上個世紀末到上個世紀初這個時間
It's in fact the first human to synthesize it in a laboratory way
它事實上它是第一個人用實驗室的合成的方式
And inventing and synthesizing a substance with a new color appears
而發明合成出一個新的顏色的物質出現
This new color material is called intrinsically safe paper
這個新的顏色的物質叫做本安紙
The color itself has this tinge of purple
這個顏色本身是帶有這種淡淡的紫色的
light purple substance
淺色的紫色的物質
We call this chemical synthesis
我們稱這個是以化學合成方式
Created the first entirely new organic dye
所創造的第一個全新的有機染料
This thing does not exist in nature
這個東西自然界並不存在
something like this structure
跟這個結構一樣的東西
and no such thing appears
並沒有這樣的東西出現
So the thing it synthesizes is colored
所以它所合成出來的這個東西是有顏色的
And it's a roughly non-existent color
而且是一個大致的並不存在的顏色
So it's a color created by humans
所以是人類創造出來的一個顏色
matter of color
顏色的物質
This is what I found in a book
這個是我從一本書中找到了
This is the internal substance that was synthesized in his laboratory at the beginning.
這個就是當初他所在實驗室裡面所合成出來的內貫物質的東西
still preserved
還保存到現在
This color is called book
這個顏色叫做本子
Yasuko Moto
本安子
This is what we now call the father of painters
這個我們現在稱為畫工之父
because you went to see his hometown
因為你去看他的家鄉
His hometown has been turned into a museum
他的家鄉已經變成一個博物館
there is a sign on it
上面有一塊牌子
If you zoom in to see him, look at him
你放大去看的話 你看他
this person is actually
這個人事實上
because he discovered the synthesis of this dye
因為他發現了這個染料的合成
One of the next things he did was
他接下來做的一個事情就是
He founded an industry based on scientific registration
他成立了一個以科學登記為基礎的工業
The meaning of this English word translated into Chinese
這個英文字翻成中文字這個意思
Science-based industry industry
Science-based industry industry
means industry
就是工業的意思
Industry didn't exist before him
工業在他之前並不存在
The painting industry we are talking about now
我們現在講的畫工業
just start with it
就是從它而開始
what great things does it do
它做了什麼偉大的事情呢
It is the self-preparation of the dye
就是它把這個染料的自備呢
Produce in large quantities Collect in large quantities
大量的生產 大量的收集下來
Then take it to the market to sell
然後拿到市面上去販賣
what color
這個顏色呢
Because the package is very similar to the purple we talked about earlier.
因為包好跟前面我們講的這個紫色非常的類似
So it's purple when we talked about it
所以它這個紫色當初我們講說
This is extracted from the carapace and very hard work
這個是從那個甲殼與很辛苦的提煉出來
You have to collect tens of thousands of things to be able to dye a little cloth
你要收集上萬格的東西才能夠染一點點的布
Now it can be mass-produced at one time by synthetic means
現在它用合成的方式一次可以大量生產出來
So the one with the color is no longer the rich and powerful
所以那個擁有色彩就不再是有錢人有權勢的人
It's something exclusive
所專門獨享的一個東西了
So here you see this is a book
所以這邊你看這是一本書啊
it says
它上面講說
a man it invented a color
一個人它發明了一種顏色
And it's like this, this, this move
而它這樣子這個這個舉動呢
changed the whole world
就改變了這整個世界
I translated it into Chinese
我把它翻成中文就是
a man invents a color
一個人發明了一個顏色
The world has changed since then
從此這個世界就因此而改觀
Thus began the chemical industry
化學工業就因此而開始誕生
that's because
就是因為
From the beginning of it we will call it the father of chemical engineering
從它開始的我們就會稱它為叫做化工之父
This is also a dye that it synthesized later.
這個也是它後來合成出來的一個染料
This dye is Qiansu
這個染料的就是倩素
is what we just saw earlier
就是我們剛剛前面看到
This thing extracted from the root of the tree
從樹根裡面所提煉出來的這個東西
identical chemical structure
一模一樣的化學結構
This is from the root of the tree
這個是從樹根裡面
extracted from natural
天然物裡面萃取出來的
This microlink thin product from the laboratory
這個微聯薄積從實驗室裡面
Prepare it by chemical synthesis
用化學合成的方式把它給自備出來
So this is so here you look up the history book
所以這個是所以這邊你查那個歷史的書
It is written that this substance is
它就有寫說這個物質是
produced by chemical synthesis
以化學合成的方式所複製出來的
The first natural organic dye
第一個天然的有機染料
This dye is found in nature
這個染料是自然界存在的
But in the past, it was extracted from the roots of trees.
但是以往都是要從樹根裡面萃取
But it is synthesized by the laboratory
但是它是由實驗室裡面去把它合成出來
And another of its inventions is
而它另外一個發明的東西是
There is no such thing in nature
自然界並不存在這樣的一個東西
completely pure matter created in the laboratory
完全純粹是從實驗室裡面所創造出來的物質
Okay, let me tell you this is simple
好 這個我跟大家說為簡單的
this is chemistry
這個是化學
How did Winter Night synthesize this dye?
冬夜界是怎麼合成這個染料的呢?
add these three things together
把這三個東西加在一起
All three are made of organic matter
這三個全部都是由有機物質所構成的
After putting these three things together
把這三個東西和在一起之後
Add running acid water and heavy acid
裡面加上流酸水再加上重落酸甲
This acts as an oxidizing agent
這個當作氧化劑
You can put these three things in this ring together to fix it together
就可以把這三個本環的東西把它定在一起
When Wenyuan International synthesized this thing
當初溫源國際合成這個東西的時候
In fact it doesn't know
事實上它不曉得了
it gets in fact a mixture
它得到事實上是一個混合物
It includes ABCD
裡面包括了ABCD
There are at least two ingredients of all sorts
各式各樣的東西至少有兩個成分
like this one I drew earlier
就像我前面畫的這個
At least two ingredients make up its pot of medicine
至少有兩個成分構成了它這一罐的藥品
chemical
化學藥品
this is colored
這個是有顏色的
In fact the dye is not a single substance
事實上這個染料並不是一個單一物質
In fact this mixture
事實上這個混合物質
It does this thing in fact it is not its original purpose
它做這個東西事實上並不是它原來的目的
write one here
這邊寫一個
What was it actually supposed to do?
它事實上本來是要做什麼?
Back then that sadism was troublesome
那時候那個虐疾很麻煩
At that time there was no medicine to treat
那時候沒有藥物可以治療
I knew at that time
那時候知道說
It is said that treating internal diseases can relieve the symptoms
說治療內疾的可以舒緩這個症狀
It is from this natural thing called
就是從這個什麼天然物叫做
The bark or roots of economical numbers
經濟那數的樹皮或樹根裡面
It can be distilled into a thing called the neighbor
可以提煉出一個這樣的東西叫做睽鄰
It can be used to treat internal diseases
睽鄰是可以用來治療內疾的疾病的
Its original purpose at that time was to find a way
它那時候原來的目的是要想辦法
This natural substance was synthesized in the laboratory
在實驗室裡面合成出這個天然物質
You can see back then because chemistry was just out
你可以看那時候因為化學還才剛剛出來
We're not that familiar with this synthesis yet.
我們對這個合成還不是那麼的熟悉
Everyone probably knows about this structure that there is a ring in it.
大家對這個結構大概知道說裡面還有本環
there are eggs in it
裡面還有蛋
There are some oxygen elements in it
裡面還有一些氧的元素在這個裡面
So it starts doing the poor job
所以它開始就去做貧臭的工作
At that time, the source it chose was to choose these three things
那時候它選擇到的來源就是選了這三個東西
to group it and put those groups
去把它組一組放那些組組
hope to get this thing
希望能夠得到這個東西
Of course it is impossible
事實上當然不可能
We know chemistry very well now
我們現在對化學很了解很清楚
It's impossible to get this thing like this
不可能這樣子就可以得到這個東西了
So its original purpose was not to be a dye
所以它原來的目的是並不是要做染料
It's actually purely for medical purposes
它事實上純粹是為了做醫療上的一個
synthetic work in education
教育的合成的工作
And the narrow false found that it got a colored substance
而狭假无状发现了它得到了有颜色的物质
You see it in a beaker with a jar of purple ejaculation in it
你看到它烧杯里面放了一罐紫色的荣液在这里面
is a drawing
是画的图
It means that it was walking around in the laboratory at that time
说明它那时候在实验室里面东弓西弄
In the end, I got a medicine that I didn't get, but I got a colored substance
最后弄出了一个没有得到的葵林的药物反而得到了有颜色的物质
its brain moves fast
它的脑筋动得很快
It wants to say that this is very similar to Taier Paper
它就想说这个跟太儿纸很像
So it can be sold on the market
所以它就可以拿到市面上去卖
So it actually retired very early
因此它事实上它很早就退休不干了
It retired in its 30s
它大概30几岁就退休不干
because it invented the dye in the 20s
因为它在20多岁的时候发明了这个染料
big money ever since
从此就赚了大钱
it just keeps working
它就持续工作
it's at home by itself
它就自己在家里面
It has set up a laboratory at home
它自己在家里面设了一个实验室
I am researching and developing various dyes by myself
自己在研究开发各式各样的染料
Because at that time around 30 years old it had already made enough money
因为那时候30岁左右它已经赚饱了钱
Just retreat into the rivers and lakes and do research at home
就退隐江湖自己在家里面做研究
this and more
这个还有更多的
this is chemical
这个是化工
Just now I said that he artificially synthesized the first natural dye
剛才那個我講說他用人工合成第一個天然的染料
He started with this substance
他是從這個物質開始做起
This substance is extracted from plum oil
這個物質是從梅椒油裡面提煉出來的
After one step, two steps and three steps you will get this
經過一步兩步三步就會得到這個
Appearance of chigusa reddish yellow dye
千草赤黃色的染料出現
The Chicasana yellow dye was made to the UK
那個千草赤黃色的染料是讓對英國的
Because that Poke-Voyance Brit
因為那個Poke-Voyance英國人
This early British floating oath has this red uniform on it
這個英國早期的浮誓上面就有這個紅色的制服
This is the dye used for dyeing
是用的就是這個染料來染色的
Well, there is another thing that is related to the material of that Thai son.
好還有一個東西就是跟那個泰兒子的物質
A very similar thing is called Indigo dye
非常相像的一個東西就叫做Indigo dye
Indigo dye we now translate it as called
Indigo dye我們現在把它翻譯成為叫做
what is this called
這個叫什麼
electric blue dye
電藍的染料
Indigo dye
Indigo dye
This thing is actually what we use to dye jeans now
這個東西呢事實上就是我們現在用在染色牛仔褲
What about the blue pigment dye that is used the most?
用的最多的那個藍色的這個色素染料呢
this is the thing
就是這個東西
This stuff is actually the same dye as Tay's son
這個東西事實上跟泰兒子的染料
The results of non-resembling
的 結果非能相像
The fetus is in these two positions
胎子是在這個兩個位置
In two more show elements
在多兩個秀的元素
You take these two show elements
你把這兩個秀的元素
after removing it
去掉之後呢
closer to blue
就比較偏近於藍色的顏色
What about the blue pigment?
這個藍色的色素呢
In fact, as we said earlier
事實上就我們前面講說
you want to get from that crustacean
你要從那個甲殼魚類
Distilling this non-functional and hard work
提煉出來這個非能而辛苦
Otherwise you have to get it from the plant
不然的話你要從這個植物裡面
This plant is called
這個植物叫做
Inside the plant of Miaolan
妙蘭這個植物裡面
This thing can also be extracted
也可以提煉出這個東西出來
But this refinement is also very troublesome
但是這個提煉也是很麻煩
to go through this
要經過這個
Heavy extraction and purification steps
沉沉的萃取跟純化的步驟
to get a little something
才能得到一點點的東西
So the chemical industry in Germany is very fresh
所以德國的化工業非常的新鮮
At that time, Germany's Basford Industries
那時候德國的巴斯福工業吧
no it's not basford
不是 這不是巴斯福
this bell
這個貝爾
Bell is actually owned by Bayer AG in Germany.
貝爾事實上是德國的拜爾公司的
the founder
這個成立者
He is also the winner of the Nobel Prize in Chemistry
他身上也是化學諾貝爾講的得主
He invented this synthetic method
他發明了這個合成的方式
It's like Tyrian paper
就是類似像泰爾紙那樣子的
color dye
顏色的染料
After these two steps, he can get
他經過這個兩個步驟可以得到
That was in 1882, over six years old
那個是在1882年 超過六歲
The era of unknown writers and artists
不明文藝人那個時代
At that time, Germany's chemical industry also began to regenerate.
那時候德國的化工業也開始新生起來
This synthesis is inconvenient
這個合成比較不方便
improved later
後來做了改進
A synthetic christian improvement made by this guy
由這個人做了一個合成基督生改進
from a less expensive precursor
由一個比較便宜的前驅物
It is easier to get this dye out
可以更容易獲得這個染料出來
This is later all changed to use
這個是後來就全部都改成用
Lugong Chemical Synthesis
輪功化學合成的方式來做
Because the chemical synthesis of Lun Gong is much better than the extraction from natural substances
因為輪功化學合成遠比從天然物萃取
Or it's much more convenient to extract from the inside of that crustacean
或是從那個甲殼魚的裡面萃取來方便多了
The price is cheap, it can be much cheaper
價錢又便宜 可以便宜很多
Anyone who has entered the era of the chemical industry
任何已經進入到化學工業的時代了
This dye was invented after such a twists and turns
這個染料是發明是經過這樣的一個波折出現的
Then we use the most truthful product now
那我們現在用了最多的一個實話的產品
It's a plastic product
就是塑膠的製品
Everyone knows that plastic products are often colorless.
那各位知道塑膠的製品往往都是沒有顏色的
But like the clothes you physically wear
但是像各位生理上穿的衣服
These are all made of the real fiber of the real product
這個都是實話產品的實話纖維做的東西
It was all colorless
原來都是沒有顏色的
why now we can wear
為什麼現在我們可以穿在身上
There are so many colors
有那麼多的色彩顏色呈現呢
because of all the plastic inside
是因為這些所有的塑膠製品裡面
The dye of ginseng is in this
都參的染料在這個裡面
plastic we can see this
塑膠製品我們可以看到這個
Whether it is PVC, PS
就是不管是PVC、PS
Di density, drama language, high-density drama language and
迪密度、劇語息、高密度劇語息跟
The drama interest and that PET
劇品息跟那個PET
The material of the PET bottle is called PET.
就是寶特瓶的這個材料叫做PET
There will be colors in it
裡面都會有顏色產生
The color without ginseng is like this
本來沒有參的顏色就是像這樣子
is white or transparent
就是白色或者是透明的
this is its original color
這是它本來的顏色
But you see these new doctors in every color
但是你看到這些新醫生的各式各樣顏色
All with added dyes or pigments
全都是在外加了染料或色素
Only after going inside will these colors appear
到裡面去之後才會呈現出這些色彩
Otherwise our world would be very dull
不然的話我們的世界就是很平淡無息
either white or black
不是白的就是黑的
Without the invention of this dye
沒有這個染料這個東西的發明的話
This is about a thing that was often published in newspapers a while ago
這個講到一個前一陣子常常上報紙的一個東西
peer ratio
同業率數那
This thing is it's a natural pigment
這個東西是它是一個天然的色素
It's a natural pigment very close to something
它是一個天然的色素很接近的一個東西
The closest natural pigment to it is the leaf green tree
跟它最接近的天然的色素就是葉綠樹
we know the natural world
我們知道大自然界
you look at the leaves of that tree
你去看那個樹木的樹葉
That is, each color of multicolored ice has its own color.
就是五彩冰的各自顏色都有
The green in it is made of this
其中的綠色是由這個
This is a natural substance
這個是天然物質
That's where the chemical structure of the chlorophyll tree is located
就是葉綠樹的化學結構就在這個地方
Look at this sodium copper chlorophyllin
你看這個同葉綠樹那
Does it look very similar to this structure?
是不是跟這個結構長得非常的像
It removes the long tail
它把這個長長的這個尾巴給去掉
then it puts
然後它把
I see this upside down
我看這個還要上下顛倒過來
Everything else looks very similar
其他的東西都長得非常的類似
There is one thing that is different
那其中有個東西不一樣就是
It puts the beautiful element of MG in the middle
它把中間這個MG這個美的元素
changed to copper
換成了銅
why is this thing called copper
為什麼這個東西叫做銅
The reason this word is in it
這個字在這裡面的原因
It is because it puts the beauty in the leafy green tree
就是因為它把葉綠樹裡面原來含有美
The metal was replaced by copper
這個金屬換成了銅
and then it's next to this
然後它在旁邊的這個
this is a sour root
這個是一個酸根
The acid radical will carry an ion with a that
酸根會攜帶有一個那的離子
in this position with
在這個位置跟
All three positions will carry acid radicals
這三個位置都會攜帶酸根
and then carry that
然後就會攜帶有那
so this position
所以這個位置
The name of this painting is called Same Ye Filter Tree Na
這個畫物的名稱叫做同葉濾樹納
I found this from the website
這個我從網站上查到就是說
I'll read it for everyone
我念一下給大家聽
Although everyone understands what it means
雖然大家都看著懂這是什麼意思
The same leaf filter refers to the leaf filter semi-synthetic
同葉濾樹納的是指葉濾樹半合成
a practical pigment
產生的一種實用色素
it's actually edible
實際上它是可以吃的
it is called natural green tree
它是叫做天然的綠色樹
number three
三號
It also has an English serial number called 1141
它還有一個英文的編號叫1141
In Taiwan, it is a practical pigment that can be added at zero clock
在台灣是可加在零時鐘的實用色素
But it cannot be added to the practical oil
但是不可以加在實用的油中
A while ago, the inner defender in the newspaper made a shameful mistake.
前陣子報紙上那個內衛人羞犯了一個錯誤就是
it adds it to utility oil
它把它加在實用油中
this is not allowed
這個是不被允許的
it's illegal
這是違法的
it is edible
它是可以吃的東西
But it cannot be added to utility oil
但是不可以加在實用油裡面
The leaf filter tree we just saw in nature
自然界我們剛剛看到的葉濾樹
The leaf filter tree is a plant that has
葉濾樹是植物裡面所具有的一個
A source of many pigments
很多的一個色素的來源
The other is that compared to plants, they are animals
另外一個就是相對於植物就是動物
what about animals
動物呢
is red because blood is red
是紅色 因為血液是紅色的
that makes these two very different colors
那造成這兩個顏色很不一樣的顏色
In fact, its chemistry is very similar
事實上它的化學物質卻是非常的類似
The following is the main structure of the leaf green tree
下面這個是葉綠樹的主要的結構
The one above is our red blood cell
上面這個是我們血紅球
Iron fingers in red blood cells
紅血球裡面的鐵指質
Red blood cells should, in fact, also be colorless
紅血球本來事實上也應該也是沒有顏色
But it contains a thing like this
但是它裡面含了一個這個東西
This thing is available in red color
這個東西是具備的是紅色的顏色
Do you see that this structure looks very similar to
你看這個結構是不是長得非常像
Except for the middle this is a beauty
除了中間這個是一個美
above is an iron
上面是個鐵之外
different metal
金屬不同之外
The structure of Zhongwei is also slightly different
中微的結構也稍微有點不太一樣
But the color is so different
但是顏色上面卻天差地遠
one is red one is green
一個是紅色 一個是綠色
This is a newspaper from two or three years ago
這個是兩三年前的一則報紙
I don't know if you guys still remember
我不曉得大家還記不記得
Looking at the body, it means that there is a daughter-in-law who wants to kill his in-laws
看表體就是說有一個媳婦下菜想害死他的公婆
what did he put in it
他在裡面加了什麼東西
He put a pinch of sour in their meal
他在他們吃飯的裡面加了咬銷酸
What is subsoleic acid?
什麼東西是亞蕭酸呢?
It's the bacon thing
就是醃肉的那個東西
Sodium nitrite chemical molecule is NANO2
亞蕭酸那化學分子是NANO2
It's the combination of Assiolic Acid and
就是亞蕭酸跟配合一個那裡
Assona
只叫有亞蕭酸那
This thing is actually an oxidizing agent
這個東西呢事實上是一個氧化劑
it will eat into the human body
它會吃到人體裡面
It will take the ferrous iron in the heme
它會把血紅素裡面那個鐵子質的那個鐵呢
the action of oxidation
進行氧化的動作
Turn Iron Two into Iron Three
把鐵二架變成鐵三架
Our human blood must be able to absorb oxygen
我們人的血液要能夠吸收氧氣
We need oxygen to breathe
我們要吸收氧氣才能夠呼吸
Rely on the second iron frame
靠的是鐵二架
Once the iron two frame is replaced by the iron three frame
一旦把那個鐵二架換成鐵三架之後
Human blood can no longer absorb oxygen
人的血液就沒有辦法再吸代氧氣了
so people die
所以人就會死掉
What are your symptoms?
你所出現的症狀呢就是
Normal blood looks red
正常人的血看起來就是紅紅的
But that's because of the iron content of Iron II
但是那是因為鐵二架的鐵子質造成的
But if you turn Iron II into Iron III
但是如果你把鐵二架變成鐵三架
What about iron quality at this time?
這時候的鐵子質呢
It looks darker
看起來顏色就比較深的
Look at the left and right hands
你看左右這兩隻手就是
It's the color of the hands of the poisoned in-laws
是中毒的那個公婆的手的顏色
because its blood can no longer absorb oxygen
是因為它的血液不再能夠吸收氧氣
At that time the report said
那時候報道講說
It was later discovered that it was because of the poison
那個後來發現說是因為中的這個毒
they are in the hospital
他們在醫院裡面
Symptoms of a poisoning like this
對這樣子的一個中毒的症狀
can add this sub
可以加上這個亞
First
甲
blue
藍
this thing
這個東西
In fact this is a finite color substance
事實上這個是一個有限顏色的物質
This thing can help put this iron shirt rack
這個東西可以幫助把這個鐵衫架
Revert back to Iron Erjia
再還原回去到鐵二架
In fact, what about this colored substance?
事實上這個有顏色的物質呢
also a potion
也是一個藥劑
In fact it can do that oxidative mixing action
事實上它可以進行那個氧化混合的動作
itself it is blue
本身它是具有藍色的
you can see it melt in the water
你可以看到它融在水
There is a blue substance in the water
水裡面是一個藍色的物質
you go
你去
If you have to look it up
你必須要去查它的用途的話
you can see it's a chemical indicator
你可以看到它是一個化學指示劑
Also a dye
同時也是個染料
because it has a color relationship
因為它有顏色的關係
It is also a biological stain
它也是一個生物染色劑
you can see this above
你可以看到這個上面
The word is the tissue of the human body
這個字是人體的組織
After applying this dye
把這個染料塗上去之後
You can see it renders this blue
你可以看到它呈現出這個藍色的
presented
呈現出來
So this release is also a dye thing
所以這個釋放也是一種染料的東西
Because as long as there is color, we can call it a dye
因為只要有顏色的我們就可以稱作為染料
And the dye is actually an antidote
而這個染料的事實上也是一個解毒劑
Once you plant this acesena poison
一旦你種了這個亞塞森納的毒
Just rely on this to detoxify
就是靠這個來解毒
This news report is headline news
這個新聞報導是上頭版頭料的新聞
There are several chemicals in it
裡面貼到了好幾個化學物質
includes this dye
包括了這個染料
This bacon is included
包括了這個醃肉的東西
In fact, this is our pool of people
事實上這個是我們人池多
this will be poisonous
這個會種毒的
with this leafy green tree or ferrite
跟這個葉綠樹或者是鐵子質
a very similar thing
很相像的一個東西
It's a synthetic thing
是人工合成出來的東西
This is a thing that is used a lot in the industry
這個是在工業界用了非常多的一個東西
Because this is completely produced by synthesis in the laboratory
因為這個完全是由實驗室裡面合成所產生出來的
These things are also dyes or pigments
這些東西也是染料或者是色素
Dye called Taiqinglin
叫做太清素的染料
Or I can see it in
或者我裡面也可以看到
It's very similar to the ferrous structure
跟那個鐵子質的結構很像
just in the four corners
只是在這個四個角落呢
Change this CH to N
把這個CH換成了N
changed to bomb
換成了彈
The structure of Yuanyuan's large plate still looks exactly the same
原原的大盤的结构还是长得一模一样
But this color is just like these four eggs
但是这个颜色就跟多了这四个蛋
It's not the same as without these four colors
就跟没有这四个的颜色又不一样了
Originally, the inside of the iron paper was red.
本来铁纸纸里面是这个是红色的
If it were changed to beauty, it might be green
如果换成美的话可能是绿色
This one has four more eggs and then replaced it with a bucket
这个呢多了四个蛋之后又换成了桶
or no bucket
或者是没有桶
The color itself is blue
这个本身的颜色是偏蓝色的
like this is very blue blue
像这个是很蓝的蓝色
or so this one is bluish
或者是这样这个是偏蓝色的
This type of substance is a pigment dye that is completely functionally synthesized.
这一类的物质呢是完全是能功合成出来的一个色素染料
This thing is much more stable than iron paper or these
这个东西呢比铁纸纸或者这些就稳定非常多
Such dyes and pigments are widely used in some optoelectronic industries
这样子的染料色素呢被广泛的用在一些光电工业里面
Let's come back to the photoelectric application later.
等一下我们再回过来讲这个光电上的应用了
Next, let's talk about the substance of this color.
接下来我们要讲这个颜色的物质呢
is about this practical pigment
是有关于这个实用色素
As we mentioned earlier, Tongye Suna
我们前面讲到同叶率素那
That is allowed to be added to the utility
那个是可以允许加在实用品里面
But it cannot be added to utility oil
但是不可以加在实用油里面
that too
那个也是
is a food coloring
是一種食用的色素
there are many things
還有很多東西
inside what we eat
我們吃的東西裡面
In order to increase the vividness of the food
為了增加食物的鮮豔的程度
Usually some coloring is added here
通常都會加一些色素在這裡面
What is allowed to be added is called
可以允許加進去的這個都叫做
Qualified edible artificial coloring
合格的可食用的人工色素
These edible artificial colors
這些可食用的人工色素
Let me give you an example
我舉個例子給大家看
I didn't know you liked this hot dog
我不知道你喜歡吃這個熱狗
This is a very standard hot dog thing
這個就是很標準的一個熱狗的東西
hot dog with bun
熱狗有麵包
there is a sausage in it
裡面有一根香腸
Then usually put this ketchup and mustard sauce
然後通常都會放上這個番茄醬跟芥末醬
Food coloring is added to mustard, ketchup, and hot dogs
芥末醬、番茄醬、熱狗裡面都加了食用的色素
Because otherwise the colors wouldn't be so bright
因為不然的話顏色不會如此的鮮豔
ketchup is red, right?
番茄醬紅色的對不對
Added this orange-red pigment in it
裡面加了這個橘紅色的色素在裡面
What about the yellow mustard?
芥末醬這個黃色呢
Added this yellow pigment inside
裡面加的是這個的黃色的色素在這裡面
There is also this orange-red pigment added to the sausage
香腸裡面也有加了這個橘紅色的色素
These three pigments are classified according to their chemical structure
這三個色素我們按照化學的結構來分類
All three are called
這三個都屬於叫做
Mouth Tears Dye
口淡淚的染料
colorful
有顏色的
one is orange
一個是橘紅色
one is yellow
一個是黃色
add to this
加在這個裡面
Can make your hot fruit look more salivating
可以讓你的熱果看起來更垂涎欲低
The color is very strong and very bright
色彩很硬力也很鮮豔
whet your appetite
會激起你的食慾
something like this
像這類的東西
are also widely used on these planet-colored
也廣泛地被使用在這些行星色色的
inside the food
吃的東西裡面
Like this is MMM's chocolate candy
像這個是MMM的巧克力糖
This is Regan's candy
這個是雷根的糖果
Called Jerry Bean
叫做Jerry Bean
There are many different colors in the edible drink
食用的飲料裡面有很多種不同的顏色
Wind model with pills
跟藥丸的風模
It is usually colored inside
裡面通常都是有顏色的
These edible artificial colors are usually added
通常都是加了這些可食用的人工色素
I remember this one is called Marco Dirty
這個我記得這個叫做馬可污
See various colors inside
裡面看到各種各樣的顏色
It's all food coloring.
通通都是裡面加的食用色素
You can easily find it online
你可以上網很容易查到的
What are these food colorings?
這些食用色素是哪些東西呢
these things
就是這些東西
The ones listed above are the pigments of silver Xu in the United States
這邊上面所列的是美國的銀許的色素
Different countries have different banking licenses
不同國家有不同的銀許
Using the United States as the standard, these chemical structures I have found out
用以美國為標準這些我有查出來的化學結構
It's all organic chemicals and they're colored
全都是有機化學物質他們是有顏色的
Some may be blue, some may be red, yellow, orange
還有的可能是藍色有的是紅色黃色橘色
These are allowed to be added to the utility
這些都是可允許加在實用品裡面的
substances that add color
增加顏色的物質
There are also some pigments that come from nature
還有些是色素是來自於天然界
For example, astaxanthin
譬如說像這個蝦紅素
In fact you can in the pharmaceutical factory
事實上你可以在藥廠
You can get this at the pharmacy
藥店買得到這個東西
it's not a drug it's a drug called like a vitamin
它不是藥它是一個叫做像維他命一樣
is a tonic thing
是一個補品的東西
It's sold inside, you can see what's inside this orange-red capsule
它賣的裡面你看這個橘紅色的膠囊裡面的
liquid is astaxanthin
液體就是蝦紅素
it puts it in oil
它把它放在油裡面
itself it is cloth body like this one
本身它是布體像這樣子一個
very dark orange-red colored powder
很暗的橘紅色的顏色的粉末
It is also an organic substance
它也是一個有機的物質
lots of doubles in it
裡面有很多雙件
Here are 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
這邊有1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
eleven, twelve, thirteen
十十一、十二、十三
From head to tail, fourteen or fifteen double swords
頭尾再下去 十四、十五個雙劍
So the wavelength of its color can be extended to
所以它的顏色的波長可以延伸到
within this range of long-wavelength red
長波長的紅色的這個範圍之內
This thing actually takes tea from nature
這個東西呢 事實上取茶於大自然界
Much more convenient than artificial synthesis
遠比人工合成方便很多
I'll check it out
我去查一下
Artificial, like this category, all substances that belong to this category are called
人工 像這一類 都是屬於這一類的物質叫做
family of carotenoid trees
類胡蘿蔔樹的家族
What's Included Beta Carrot Tree
包括什麼 北塔胡蘿蔔樹
yellow tree including corn leaves
包括玉米葉的黃樹
What we saw before me looks like this
我前面我們看到的像都是這樣子
This is actually produced from the algae itself
這個事實上從這個藻類它本身就會產生
Obtain the pigment of the shrimp mangrove like this from this algae
從這個藻類獲得這樣子的蝦紅樹的色素
Much simpler than synthetic
遠比人工合成來得簡單很多
Because the synthesis is more troublesome
因為這個合成比較麻煩
so this thing especially this thing
所以這個東西 特別是這個東西
We won't be so stupid as to say we synthesize it ourselves in the lab
我們不會笨到說在實驗室裡面自己合成
Because it will cost more to synthesize it yourself
因為這個自己合成反而會更花錢
to do the synthetic work
來做這個合成的工作
this is
這個是
It is some steps of artificial synthesis
是人工合成的一些步驟
you see very troublesome
你看到非常的麻煩
many steps
很多步驟
So it's better to go find that naturally
所以還不如去天然找那個
Looking for a class?
找類呢
The convenience of extracting from looking for classes
從找類來萃取來的方便
What about the same substance?
這個同類的物質呢
Also includes this nightshade tree and carrot tree
也包括這個茄紅樹還有胡蘿蔔樹
that yellow
那種黃色
orange-yellow substance
橘黃色紅色的物質
All belong to this category
通通都屬於這類的
Substances of this family
這類家族的物質
There is another kind of colored
還有另外一類有顏色的
These are the fruits we often eat
就是我們常吃的這些水果
this dark fruit
這個顏色很深的水果
like blueberries or grapes
像什麼藍莓啊葡萄
Eggplant Helizi
茄子黑莉子啊
This is a dye that contains the same pigment
這個都含有這個同樣的一種色素的染料
This is called a flower tree
這個都叫做花青樹
These are usually reddish substances
通常都是偏紅色的這些的物質
What about this flower tree?
這個花青樹呢
there is another thing
還有另外一種東西呢
also often appear
也常常出現
somewhat similar to that structure
跟那個結構有點類似的
called the color inside the hydrangea
叫做繡球花裡面的顏色
hydrangea inside color
繡球花裡面顏色
It also contains this anthocyanin tree
就是也是含有這個花青樹
The top of the structure of the anthocyanin tree
花青樹的結構上面
His color will follow the color of your soil
他的顏色會隨著你的土壤的
Variations in acidity and alkalinity
酸鹼度的不同而出現有變化
This is a substance that belongs to the color of nature
這個是屬於大自然的色澤的物質
ok this is his time
好 這個是他時間
about ten minutes
還有大概十分鐘時間
In more than ten minutes, I took the second half of this
十多分鐘我把這個後半段
finish it
把它講完
I'm going to talk about it next
接下來就要講到說
These we have talked about so far are called
這些我們講到目前為止都是叫做
traditional dyeing and finishing process
傳統的染整工藝
The dyes we use are usually for coloring
我們取用的染料通常都是來著色
make things come out in color
讓東西有呈現顏色出來
This is a more traditional approach
這個是比較傳統的一個做法
What about the current technology?
現在的科技呢
actually go one step further
事實上就更推進一步
We're no longer talking about color
我們不再是說為了呈現出顏色
We are using some of its photoelectric characteristics
我們是利用它的一些光電上面的特性呢
same color
一樣是呈現顏色
but we're using it for this
但是我們是把它用在這個
Inside the optoelectronic components
光電的元件裡面
TV-like color rendering
像電視機的顏色的呈現
The presentation of the color of the mobile phone panel
手機面板的顏色的呈現
Also like what you see here
還有像這邊看到的
The discs we use to record data
我們用來記錄資料的光碟片
These dyes are actually used in it.
裡面事實上都有用到這些染料
This is more modern and not traditional
這個是比較現代進一步的不像傳統的
Let's talk about the traditional dyeing and printing process
我們講說傳統的染印的工藝
Now it means that it is applied to optoelectronic technology
現在變成是說應用在光電科技上面
Although this technology is a bit outdated
雖然這個技術也已經有點過時了
But this was considered a very
但是這個在十多年前算是一個很
More than ten years ago, twenty years ago, it was considered a very popular new technology
十多年前 二十年前算是一個很熱門的一個新的技術
It is a technology for storing data
就是儲存資料的一個技術
It's the CD.
就是那個光碟資料片
In fact, there is a layer of dye in it.
裡面事實上都有放了一層染料在這個裡面
Look at this English word, low crooked one means dye
你看看這個英文字 低歪一 就是染料的意思
In the middle it is a very thin multilayer film
中間它是一個很薄的一個多層的薄膜
One of the layers is the substance of this dye
其中有一層就是這個染料的物質
The reason why it can record is that this dye absorbs
它之所以能夠記錄就是靠了這個染料吸收
We need to use a laser light to do the action of burning the road
我們需要用到一個雷射光去做燒路的動作
it will absorb this laser light
它會吸收這個雷射光
And the dye in this place will go bad
而這個地方的染料就會變質
so need
所以需要
Substances that receive laser light
接收雷射光的物質
Laser light is also a kind of light
雷射光也是光的一種
a type of visible light
可見光的一種
So this basically needs to rely on dyes
所以這個基本上都是需要靠染料
In order to be able to achieve this application
才能夠辦得到這個這方面的應用
well everyone knows this
好這個大家知道
There are two types of discs
這個光碟片有分兩種
One piece is 500Mbz
一個是一片是500Mbz
For DVD2, it is several Gigabytes larger
那DVD2的話更大是好幾個Gigabyte
The storage space varies in size
儲存的空間大小不一樣
depending on the dye used in it is not the same
取決於它裡面所用的染料不太一樣
like the dye used in CD2
像CD2裡面用的染料
Usually one of these three
通常就是這三個其中的一種
DVD2's dye is a fact
DVD2的染料是個事實上
I can't argue with this information
還吵不好這個資料
Because this is a winter night secret
因為這個算是冬夜的機密
wait you will do
等你會做的
I don't want to tell you what exactly it is used for
不願意告訴你它用的到底是什麼
we just know
我們只曉得說
It uses these two types of dyes
它用的是這兩類的染料
Synin's Dye or Azol Metal Dye
Synin的染料或是Azol Metal Dye
This Azol is what we saw earlier
這個Azol就是我們前面看到說
Yellow game dye to paint roads
拿來塗馬路的黃色的遊戲的染料
is one of a kind
是其中的一種
That one is also called Azol Dye
那個也是叫做Azol Dye
it just exists
它就是存在的
Hot dog, what, what?
熱狗啊那個這個什麼
What about the color in ketchup and mustard?
番茄醬跟芥末醬裡面的那個顏色呢
It is also a kind of dichotic dye that belongs to the Azure band
也是屬於Azure帶的一種偶膽力的染料
This Traner dye is also used in the production of this DVDR
跟這個Traner染料也用在這個DVDR的製作上面
Next, this is really about optoelectronic technology.
再來就是這個真的是講到光電科技了
The reason why our LCD screen can show color
我們LCD的螢幕之所以能夠呈現出色彩
In fact, a thing called a color-producing green light film is used in it.
事實上裡面用到了一個東西叫做產色綠光片
This is a presentation of complementary colors
這個是一個互補性的顏色的呈現
The color-producing green film is to green out the color we don't want
產色綠光片就是把我們不要的顏色給綠掉
Then filter out the color we want to see
然後把我們要看到的顏色給過濾出來
This is a display of a complementary color that is a color that cancels out
這是一個互補色就是消去型的色彩的顯示
This green light film needs to use some colored substances
這個綠光片裡面需要用到一些有顏色的物質
to absorb the colors we don't want
來把我們不要的顏色給吸收下來
For example, the screen display usually has three colors: red, blue and green.
譬如說螢幕顯示裡面通常都是紅藍綠三種顏色
So if you want to see red, you have to follow blue
所以你要看到紅的話就必須要把藍的跟進去
remove the green ones
綠的給去掉
So for example like this is a green dye
所以譬如說像這個是一個綠色的染料
the reason it's green
它之所以會呈現出綠色
Because it absorbs red and blue
是因為它把紅的跟藍的給吸收掉
so a green coloring or dye needs to be used in it
所以裡面需要用到一個綠色的色素或染料
this is its option
這個就是它的選項
In the current LCD technology
目前這個LCD的技術裡面
The green light film used in this
用到的這個產生綠光片裡面
What about this green pigment?
遇到這個綠色的色素呢
just use this thing
就是用了這個東西
This is what blue is used for
藍色呢就用的是這個東西
This is what we just saw
這個東西就是我們剛剛前面看到的
this thing
這個東西
CUPC
CUPC
This is one that is produced in millions of metric tons per year
這個是每年以幾百萬公噸在生產的一個
A very useful coloring used in the craft world
工藝界用的一個很有用的一個色素
Because it appears blue or cyan color
因為它呈現出來是藍色或是青色的顏色了
This substance is very stable
這個物質呢很穩定
So it can be used on the green light film of this LCD
所以可以用在這個LCD的產生綠光片上面
This is CUPC
就是這個CUPC
the same substance
同樣一個物質
it's a
它這是一個
a blue pigment
藍色的一個色素
Red is made of such a substance
紅色用的是這樣的一個物質
This substance is also used in the paint of the car
這個物質是它也是用在汽車的烤漆上面
orange red we saw that before
橘紅色我們之前看到那個
Maforomio's baking paint is also used by some companies
Maforomio的烤漆也有的公司用的是這個色素
painted on the top of the car
塗在車子的上面
Because these three pigments are very stable
因為這三個色素都非常的穩定
It can be stored for a long time without deterioration
它可以放很久都不會變質
Even under the light of LCE
即使被LCE的光線照射之下
it won't break
它都不會壞掉
Therefore, the reason why the LCD screen can present a variety of colors
所以LCD的螢幕之所以能夠呈現出各式各樣的色彩
With this color filter
靠著這個彩色濾光片
The color filter relies on these three pigments
而彩色濾光片裡面就靠著這三種色素
Red, blue and green pigments to filter out unwanted light colors
紅的藍的綠的色素來過濾掉不要的光色
This way you can piece together a variety of
這樣的話你就能夠拼湊出各式各樣的
colorful lin red color
七彩霖紅的顏色
good this
好這個
we've been talking so far
我們講到目前為止都在講說
Eliminate the application of models or complementary colors
消去型號或是互補色的應用
Include this app in solar tv
包括這個應用在太陽能電視裡面的
dyes are also used
也用到了染料
This dye also utilizes the erasing type
這個染料也是利用那個消去型
Or the color of the complementary color appears
或是護補色的顏色呈現出來
we talked about it from the beginning
我們一開始就講過說
things will show dye
東西會呈現出染料
It's all caused by sunlight
都是因為太陽光所造成的
As long as a certain color of sunlight is absorbed
只要太陽光的某一個顏色被吸收掉
This thing will show up in color
這個東西就會呈現出顏色出來
The colors that appear are called complementary colors
呈現出顏色我們稱呼叫護補色
For example, as you see this is translucent
譬如說像你這邊看到這個是半透明的
inside these things
這些東西裡面
yellow like this one
像這個呈現出黃色
That is, it absorbs the cyan color
就是它把青色的顏色給吸收掉
To show its complementary color is to show yellow
呈現出它的護補色就是呈現出黃色
able to appear red
能夠呈現出紅色
It is to absorb its protective color
就是把它的護補色給吸收掉
In this case, it will appear that what is left is the red color.
這樣的話就會呈現出留下的就是紅色的顏色
This is what we are currently doing research on
這個算是我們目前在做研究
Various colors that are often used
常常在用到的各式各樣的顏色
we are designing
我們就在設計說
What color material can absorb sunlight
怎麼樣的顏色的物質可以吸收太陽光
The more you absorb sunlight, the more you think about this effect.
吸收太陽光越想這個效
The higher the efficiency of the panel it can battery
它能電池的面板的效率就會越高
So this is a comparison
所以這個算是一個比較
The application of a technology that is still in the research stage
還在研究階段的一個科技的應用
good
好
we just talked about so far
我們剛剛講說講到目前為止
We're talking about what's called an evanescent color representation.
我們講的都是叫做消去式的色彩的呈現
is what we see is a complementary color
就是我們看到的是個互補色
Next, the last ten or so slides will talk about additive color
接下來最後這大概十張投影片要講的是加成性的色彩
A phenomenon in which additive color is opposite to subtractive color
加成性色彩跟消去性色彩的方式相反的一個現象
if we want to see blue
我們如果要看到藍色
We are the blue light
我們就是打上藍色的光
that is blue
那就是藍色
Green light is green
打上綠色的光就是綠色
Red light is red
打上紅色的光就是紅色
All three light colors play together
三個光色都打在一起
what is that
那就是什麼
just white
就是白色的
This is an additive color
這個是一個加成性的色彩
red green plus white
紅的綠的加白的
Basically red, yellow green, blue electronic paper
基本上就是紅色、黃綠、藍電紙
all added up
全部都加在一起
it's sunlight
就是太陽光
So in fact sunlight is also an additive color display
所以事實上太陽光也是一個加成性的色彩的顯示
So what we just said so far
所以我們剛才講到目前為止
They're all talking about elimination-type complementary colors
都是在講消去型的色彩互補色
But we're going back now to the sun at the beginning
但是我們現在又回過頭來講到一開始的太陽光
Sunlight is an additive color
太陽光就是一個加成性的色彩
Because the application of matter that we are going to talk about next
因為接下來我們要講的物質的應用
Especially the optoelectronic technology industry uses additive colors
尤其是光電科技業用的都是加成性的色彩
using a luminous substance
使用的是發光的物質
Luminous matter is like the sun
發光物質就像太陽
the sun is something that shines
太陽是發光的東西
Luminous substances are all additive colors
發光的物質都是屬於加成性的色彩的呈現
for example like this
譬如說像這個
In the laboratory, some so-called nanoparticles will be made
實驗室裡面會做一些所謂的奈米顆粒
This is a nanoparticle made of inorganic material
這個是由無機材料所做的奈米顆粒
Then we talked about it at the beginning
那我們一開始講過
Color rendering of inorganic materials
無機材料的顏色的呈現
and the size of its constituent elements
跟它的構成的元素的大小
The size of the radius is related to
半徑的大小有關係
So look at the various colors it presents here
所以你看它這邊呈現出來的各式的顏色
It is caused by the size of the nanoparticle
就是看這個奈米顆粒的大小所造成的
The bigger the color, the more reddish it will be
做得越大的顏色就會越往紅色方向偏
the smaller you make
你做得越小的話
This is towards the blue direction
這個就往藍色方向偏
but this is
但是這個是
What you see is an additive color
各位看到的是一個加成性的色彩
it's something that emits light
它是會發出光線出來的東西
This material called silver light or aura
這種叫做銀光或靈光的材料
This is the presentation of additive color
這個都是加成性色彩的呈現
Substances that include these long-lasting auras
包括這些長時間的靈光的物質
It's pretty standard like this
像這個都是很標準的
Silver light, for example, we painted on that clock
銀光譬如說我們塗在那個時鐘上面
That or the emergency exit thing that lights up
那個或者緊急出口那個會亮的東西
They are all luminous substances composed of these inorganic elements.
都是由這些無機的元素所構成的發光的物質
and inside these plastic panels
還有加在這些塑膠板子裡面
something that looks a lot like the light colors of a neon sign
那種看起來很像霓虹燈的光色的東西
It's all made of silvery material
全都是銀光的物質所構成的
It also includes going to a concert like this or that
還有包括像這個那個去聽演唱會
Don't you take two bright sticks?
不是會拿兩個會亮的那個棒子嗎
It's all made of these organic substances that have undergone chemical reactions.
那裡面全都是由這些有機的物質起了化學反應
the light emitted
所激發出來的光線
seen by our eyes
被我們眼睛看到
What we're talking about here are all so-called additive colors.
這邊我們講的全都是所謂的加成性的色彩
Most of the additive colors are composed of silver or aura substances
而加成性的色彩大部分都是由銀光或者是靈光的物質所構成的
There is also a silver light silver light
還有還有一個銀光銀光
Where the application of silver light or aura is used
銀光或靈光的應用的地方是用來
make your white look whiter
讓你的白色看起來更白
This is used because we people like pure white color very much
這個是用在因為我們人很喜歡純白的顏色
including my sports socks
包括我的運動襪子
be very white
白要非常的白
whiter whiter
越白越白
The better it is, the more beautiful it is
越好,就表示說越漂亮
There are also these clothes, you can see that there are these additives in this washing powder
還有像這些衣,你看這個洗衣粉裡面就有了這些添加物在這個裡面
Under ultraviolet light it will appear blue light
在紫外光下面它會呈現出藍色的光線
The paper towels used in our toilets are also screw-shaped
我們廁所裡面用的插手紙也是螺旨
I won't add this thing to hand paper, because it doesn't need to be very white
插手紙不會加這個東西,因為不需要很白
Because the paper towels are usually yellowish
因為插手紙通常都是偏黃色的東西
But our print is like this paper
但是我們的印像這張紙
The paper used for printing should be laid out better
印刷用的這個紙要越擺越好
This fluorescent substance must be added inside
裡面就必須要添加這個螢光的物質
as seen in this picture
像這個圖裡面看到
On the right is the hand paper, this is A4 printing paper
右邊是插手紙,這個是A4的印表紙
A4 printing paper will emit blue light when viewed under ultraviolet light
A4的印表紙在紫外光照一看就有藍色的光會發射出來
this one doesn't
這個就沒有
So in the case of blue light emitted
所以在藍色的光發射出來的情形之下
This white will look whiter
這個白色就會看起來更白
This is called a fluorescent additive, or a fluorescent whitening agent
這個叫做螢光添加劑,或者叫做螢光真白劑
This thing will be used in many places
這個東西很多地方都會用到它
Including the paper we just talked about
包括我們剛剛講看到這個紙張
Including that cloth like that white one
包括像那個繁傳的白色的那個布
to look white
因為要看起來很白
So it must add this thing
所以它一定要加這個東西
will look whiter
才會看起來更白
There are also many electrical supplies like that
還有像那個很多電系用品
It's inside the white shell
就是白色的殼子裡面
Added all of these
都通通都加了這些
The so-called fluorescent whitening agent
所謂的螢光真白劑
This has an effect of making the white whiter whiter
這個有讓白的更白的一個效果的產生
Including the white sneakers too
包括那個白色的球鞋也是
This fluorescent whitening agent is added to everything.
裡面通通都加了這個螢光真白劑
The last display
最後這個顯示器
I will quickly talk about this ten-year relationship
這個十年關係我很快的講過去
This has been eliminated
這個是已經被淘汰掉的
The display method of impression tube
印象管的顯示的方式
It actually uses a lot of this
裡面事實上用了很多這個
fluorescent powder in this
螢光粉在這個裡面
This is also a display of color called additive
這也是叫做加成性的色彩的顯示
The same is true for TVs including this plasma
還有包括這個電漿的電視也都是如此
All rely on the glow of its fluorescent powder
都是靠著它的螢光粉末的發光
to present this picture
來呈現出這個畫面的
This is plasma or impression tube
這個但是電漿或者是印象管的
In fact, they have all been eliminated
事實上都已經被淘汰掉了
there is another
另外還有一個
What this light-emitting display will use is
這個發光型的顯示器會用到的東西就是
We see this LED light bulb everywhere now
我們現在到處都可以看到這個LED的燈泡
This is also a light-emitting photoelectric product
這個也是屬於發光型的光電的產品
Some semiconductor materials are used in it.
裡面用到了一些半導體的物質所構成的
substances composed of these elements
這些元素所構成的物質
These substances after passing the current
這個這些物質在通路電流之後
it sparks light out
它會激發出光線出來
This phenomenon is called electroluminescence
這個現象叫做電積發光
Because the substances used here are all inorganic compounds
因為這邊所用到的物質都是屬於無機的化物
You can see that there is no carbon, hydrogen, oxygen and nitrogen in this
你可以看到這個裡面沒有含有碳氫氧氮這些
elements in organic matter
有機物質所含有的元素
So these substances are inorganic materials
所以這些物質是無機的材料
It can be used as a light-emitting material for LED bulbs
它是可以用來作為LED燈泡的發光的材料使用
This LED light bulb can also be used as a screen
這個LED燈泡式道也可以當作螢幕
This screen is super large and placed on that TV
這個螢幕都是超大型的放在那個電視
It's for the big screen on the wall
放在那個牆壁上面那麼大的螢幕來用的
This is like this popular place in Taipei City
這個像這個台北市這個行門地
And this is the NASDAQ CPPCC exchange
還有這個這是美國納斯達克的政協交易所
150% of this big Taipei City
一個五成這個大台北市
They're a video wall six stories high
他們是六層樓高的一個電視墻
are lined up with LED bulbs
都是由LED的燈泡所排列出來的
We just looked at a few very common
我們剛剛看了幾個很常見的
flat panel display
平面顯示器
Includes traditional acoustic tubes
包括傳統的音響管
including deprecated
包括已經不再受到歡迎的
plasma display
電漿的顯示器
What still exists is this LCD
目前還仍然存在的就是這個LCD
LCD is not an additive color display
LCD並不是一個加成性的色彩的顯示
It is a complementary color display
它是一個互補色的顯示
Because it's light passing through this colored green light sheet
因為它是光透過這個彩色綠光片
and filter out the colors we want to see
和過濾出我們要看到的顏色
This is a complementary color display
這是一個互補性的色彩顯示
The last thing I want to talk about is a flat panel monitor
最後我要講的一個平面顯示器
It is the so-called LED made of organic materials.
就是所謂用有機材料做的LED
Just now we saw that this LED is made of inorganic materials
剛才我們前面看到這個LED是無機材料做的
It is because it is composed of these inorganic elements
是因為是這些無機元素所構成的
In recent years, it has begun to appear
現在最近這幾年開始出現的
It is an electric exposure display made of organic materials
是用有機的材料做的電際曝光的顯示器
Where is this display used for?
這個顯示器用在什麼地方呢
Both of these were also eliminated.
兩個這個也都被淘汰掉了
Now
現在
Only these two things are still available in the market
只剩下這兩個東西還在市面上看得到
Should have killed it didn't kill it
應該把它殺掉沒殺掉
see next
看下一個
This was the front page headline in that newspaper a few years ago
這是前幾年那個報紙上的頭版頭條
this samsung it spends a lot of money on a full page front page
這個三星它花了大筆錢在整頁的頭版
when that ad
當那個廣告
because they made this
因為他們出了這個
This Galaxy Note
這款的Galaxy Note
With this Galaxy S smartphone
跟這個Galaxy S的智慧手機
What is used here is called organic light-emitting secondary
這裡面用到的都是叫做有機的發光二級體
Referred to as OLED
簡稱為叫做OLED
Now this OLED can be made into a 77-inch large electronic machine
現在這個OLED已經可以做到77吋的大電子機
This one was recently in Las Vegas, USA
這個是最近在美國勞斯維加斯的
Displayed in the Electronic Communications Exhibition
電子通信展裡面所展示的
LG shows in this
LG在這個裡面展示的
Just like an LCD, it can be made into such a large electronic machine
就像LCD一樣可以做成那麼大的一個電子機
And it's still made into a curved surface
而且它還是做成一個曲面的
very attractive
非常的吸引人
Compared with OLD, this LCD has some advantages.
這個LCD跟OLD比起來是有它的一些優點存在
I won't talk about the time relationship
時間關係我不再多講
Its picture is clearer
它的畫面比較清楚
It has a wider viewing angle
它的視角比較大
That camera is still relatively power efficient.
那個攝影機還是比較省電
It also has a relatively large Indian number
還有它的印達數也比較大
These organic LEs can also be used as white light
這些有機的LE也可以拿來做白光
White light means that you add red, blue, and green together
白光就是說你把紅的藍的綠的加在一起
it will turn white and you can use it for lighting
就會變成白色 可以用它做照明使用
Just like the energy-saving light bulbs in our house, we can use this instead
就像我們屋領的省電燈泡 可以用這個來代替
This glowing substance, these are all organic substances
這個會發光的物質 這些全都是有機物質
It must be synthesized in the laboratory
是要靠實驗室裡面合成出來
Just like Wayne Perkins synthesized in the laboratory
就像Wayne Perkins當年他在實驗室裡面合成
He wants to synthesize the medicine of kulin
他想要合成葵林的藥物
At that time, because he couldn't figure it out, he didn't understand the chemistry
那時候他因為他搞不清楚 他不懂這個化學
Now we know very well
現在我們懂得很懂的話
It must be designed according to his chemical structure
一定要針對他這個化學結構來設計
Because different chemical structures will show different colors
因為不同的化學結構就會呈現出不同的顏色
Like the one on the right hand side is red and orange
像這邊右手邊是紅的橘的
Yellow and green in the middle and blue on the left
中間是黃的綠的 左邊是藍的
Different chemical structures will produce different light colors
不同的化學結構就會有不同的光色產生
Organic light-emitting diodes require a variety of different
而有機發光二級體就是需要各式各樣不同的
Luminous substances to match to make the whole screen
發光的物質來搭配起來做整個螢幕
This is the end
最後這個算是到此為止
The second chapter talks a lot because I'm a chemist
第二章講了很多號因為我是化學家
I went to take a few photos in our laboratory
我去特別拍了幾張我們實驗室裡面
Photos of chemical synthesis for everyone to see
做化學合成的照片給大家看一看
Start with the simplest glass bottle
從最簡單的玻璃瓶子開始
What we ended up with is this material that glows red
我們最後做出來是這個會發出紅色螢光的材料
But this red fluorescent material was originally something like this
但是這個紅色螢光的材料一開始是這樣的一個東西
Reflected to a stage like here
像這邊反映到一個階段
a can of stuff that becomes usima black
變成烏西馬黑的一罐東西
What you want is from inside a can of this usima black
你要的東西是從這個烏西馬黑的一罐裡面去
separate it
把它分離出來
You see this red substance over here
你看這個紅色物質在這上面
There will be yellow and green fluorescent substances in the same can
同一罐東西裡面會產生黃的還有綠的螢光的物質
You use this separation technique
你利用這個分離的技術
after separating it
把它分開來之後
Collect this jar separately
把這一罐在單獨收集下來
After removing the solvent
把溶劑去除掉之後
solid will produce
固體就會產生
We collect it in this glass bottle
我們把它收集在這個玻璃瓶裡面
This is a typical chemistry lab
這個是一個很典型的化學實驗室
A practice of synthetic materials
合成材料的一個做法
This is what we use modern chemical technology
這個是我們用現代的化學科技技術
Prepare this colored substance by yourself
自備出這個有顏色的物質出來
It's just that this is an invention
只是這個是一個發明的東西
Its light-type material is the same as that of Perkin William 150 years ago
它光型的物質跟150年前Perkin William的
Of course it can't be the same
當然不可以同日而語了
they don't have that modern equipment
它們沒有那麼現代化的設備
There is no chemical laboratory like it is available now
也沒有現在這樣子的化學實驗室可以用
This is an example of our own actual
這個是我們實驗室自己實際上的一個例子
We designed and synthesized a chemical substance like this
我們設計合成了這樣子一個化學物質出來
it is fluorescent red
它是發紅色的螢光
It can be made inside this element of the red OLED
它可以製作在紅色的OLED的這個元件裡面
Is it a pixel like this?
是這樣子的一個畫素呢
It is used in Samsung smartphones
就是用在三星的智慧手機裡面
It's just that there are about 600 such things on the panel of the mobile phone
只是它這個手機面板上面大概有600顆的這樣一個東西
stuffed in here
塞在這裡面
Each one is made very small
每一顆都做得很小很小
So the resolution of this picture can be increased to a very high
所以它這個畫面的解析度可以提高到很高
We are not a panel
我們不是一個做面板的
We're just demonstrating in the lab that
我們只是在實驗室裡面示範說
we can do it too
我們也可以辦得到
We just made a big one, which is easier to make.
我們就做了很大一顆這樣比較好做了
A real panel phone needs millions of pieces to squeeze it inside
真正的面板手機是要幾百萬顆的把它擠在裡面
So each one is made very, very small
所以每一顆都做得非常非常的小
This can be regarded as the summary of the last report of today’s knowledge miss
這個算是今天這個知識的想念的一個最後的一個報告的總結了
I'm talking about dyes from that
我從那個在講染料嘛
From the traditional dyeing and finishing process
從傳統的染疫染染整工藝
The inventor is this William Bergin
這個發明人就是這個威廉伯京
We now call him the father of chemical engineering
我們現在稱他為化工之父
The production of the original dyes was based on the application of its disappearing color presentation
當初的染料的產生都是在應用它的消去式的色彩的呈現
Speaking of the application of optoelectronics in the future?
講到後面的光電的應用呢
Everything becomes the presentation of additive colors
統統都變成加成性的色彩的呈現
Either subtractive or additive
不管是消去式或者加成性
These colored substances are used
都用到了這些有顏色的物質
One is the color of bone protection
一種是就是護骨色的顏色
One is the color of the light it emits
一個是它自己發出來的光線的顏色
I will talk about the application of this fashionable technology later.
這個後面就講到說現在這個時尚的科技的應用
Includes various panels
包括各式的面板
The panel of the mobile phone or the screen of the laptop
手機的面板或者是筆電的螢幕
Or now we see that they have done the electronic machine 77 inches
或者現在我們看到他們已經做到的電子機77吋
Such a large electronic screen can be used with these luminous substances
那麼大的電子機螢幕都可以用這些發光物質來使用
In addition, it is still in the development stage
還有就是包括目前還是在研發階段的
Solar cells are also the last manifestation of the application of these dyes
太陽能電池也是這些染料的應用的最後的體現
This era has progressed from about 150 years ago.
這個時代進步從大概150多年前吧
William Perkins to the present technology transition
William Perkins到現在這個技術的轉變
It's actually I think it's unbelievably hot
是實際上是我覺得是燙為觀止的
You would never have thought to say
你在當初絕對不會想到說
These dyes can be applied to current technologies like these
這些染料可以應用在像這些現在的科技上面
Well, it's almost time now
好 現在時間也差不多到了
Ok, thank you Dr. Chen for the wonderful colorful world
好 謝謝陳博士的精彩的彩色世界
Now you are welcome to ask questions
那現在歡迎大家發表問問題
please
請
Thank you teacher Caiying for teaching me twice that one should be two lottery draws
謝謝老師兩次彩影講我一個應該是兩個抽獎的問題
There should be a problem with improving the color
應該是有提高色彩的問題
You should also remember if you reversed the color or said that you were bathed
如果反色的話或是說被洗澡的話你應該也記得
I see I see so it's too hot girl
我看到我看到 所以就太火女俠
Everything is reflected, what I see is white
全部都反射 我看的是白的
but sometimes i see
但是有時候我看到
I'll try it if it's a color bomb black
我試一下 如果是色彈黑的
But obviously there is too much fire shining on it
但是明明有太火照上去
I still think it is
我還是會覺得是
but say so
但是照著說
It's supposed to be black and suck all the light out
它應該要黑色的就把所有光都吸掉
is it?
就是嗎
I just want to ask
我只會想請教
why say still
為什麼要說還是
You said this situation is actually
你講這個情形事實上
It is absorbing and reflecting at the same time
它就是同時有吸收又有反射
coexist at the same time
同時並存
The example I just gave is very
我剛才前面舉的例子是非常
The dichotomy is that there is reflection and there is no absorption
二分法 就是有反射就沒有吸收
Or if there is absorption there is no reflection
或者有吸收就沒有反射
In fact most things are both
事實上大部分的東西是兩者並存
So you're clearly a black thing
所以你明明是黑色的東西
You can still see its light reflected
你還是可以看到它的光線被反射出來
and its reflection
而且它的反射
Because its surface is very flat
因為它這個表面弄得非常的平整
Very flat surfaces reflect light easily
非常平的表面就會很容易反射光
But it's transparent again
但是它的又是透明的東西
so it has part of the light
所以它有一部分的光
actually penetrates through
事實上就穿透過去
absorbed by its dye
被它的染料給吸收掉
appear black
呈現出黑色
But there is some light
但是又有部分光呢
it doesn't pass through
它就沒有傳透進去
it is the surface
它就被那個表面
smooth things are reflected
平滑的東西給反射出來
So you'll see this sickness
所以你會看到這種病存的現象
obviously black
明明是黑的
Why can I still see the light reflected?
為什麼還是可以看得到光反射出來
Then you can send more
那你就多寄個來一下
Because like us a kettle keeps filling
因為像我們一個水壺一直灌水
then it will break
然後會破掉
The balloon keeps inflating
氣球一直灌氣
will break
會破掉
that light is energy
那光是能量
That one assumes the black car is over there
那一個假設黑色的車子在那邊
it's shiny
它表面那個閃亮
Always absorbing, always absorbing, always absorbing
一直吸光一直吸光一直吸光
Why doesn't it seem broken or broken
為什麼不會好像破掉或壞掉
Because that energy is not yet big enough
因為那個能量還沒有大到
like that
那樣子的程度
But it keeps absorbing light and always absorbing light
但是它一直吸光一直吸光
An accompanying series is
一個附帶的系列就是
it's getting hotter and hotter
它會越來越燙越來越燙
But it's so hot that it doesn't mean that the temperature keeps going up.
但是它那個燙不會說一直溫度上去
it goes to a point
它到了一個程度
Because the object itself is exposed to sunlight
因為本身物體受到太陽光的
exposure to light
光線的照射
it emits heat
它會散發出熱能
it will reach a balance
它會達到一個平衡
It is also dissipating heat
它也同時在散熱
light keeps shining
光線一直照
It also keeps cooling
它也一直在散熱
watch this at last
最後就看這個
The total energy and its released energy will finally reach a balance
共幾的能量跟它舒散的能量最後會達到一個平衡
For example, most of our experience is
譬如說大部分我們的經驗就是
under the sun
在大太陽底下
The body of the car will be sunburned, right?
車子的車殼會被曬得很胖對不對
That temperature is about 50 degrees C
那個溫度大概就50度C左右
The degree of heat dissipation has something to do with your material.
那個散熱的程度又跟你的就是材料有關係了
Most of them will reach a stage of equilibrium
那大部分都會達到一個平衡的階段
If you really use very strong light to illuminate, for example, laser light
你如果真的拿很強很強的光去照射譬如說用雷射光
That heat is far greater than its ability to relax
那個熱量就是遠大於它的舒散的能力
Your metal will be melted away, right?
你那個金屬就會被融化掉對不對
This depends entirely on whether your input and output have reached a balance
這個完全看你的input跟output是不是有達到一個平衡的
ask holy teacher
請教聖老師
The dyes that everyone sells are for visible light absorption and reflection
大家推銷的染料是針對可見光吸收反射的走走
developed
發展出來
Are there any dyes for invisible light
那有沒有染料是針對不可見光
have
有
I just don't remember saying
我只是記得沒有講
because
因為
We can't see without light
不可見光我們就看不到了
Today I mainly focus on what we can see with our eyes
我今天主要是針對我們眼睛看得到
usually visible light
通常都是可見光
Then what you're talking about is, for example, the light outside the arc of a mirror.
那你講的就是譬如說像鏡弧外光
Or infrared light and ultraviolet light
或者紅外光跟紫外光
it is also part of the light
它也是光的一部分
but our eyes can't see
但是我們眼睛看不到
But this one has a dye like this
但是這個有這樣的染料就是
If it is a luminous dye
如果是發光型的染料的話
That is, the wavelength of your light should exceed about 700 nanometers
就是你的發光的波長要超過大概700個耐米
That is the infrared light, the mirror arc or the outer light of the mirror arc.
那個就是紅外光 鏡弧或者是鏡弧外光
If its wavelength is shorter than about 450
如果它的波長是短於大概450左右
that becomes ultraviolet light
那就變成是紫外光
Then it's about solar cells
那跟著有關的就是有關太陽能電池
Because visible light makes up only a small fraction of the
因為可見光只占一小部分的
yes
沒錯
So if it's the dye
那假如說是這種染料
Is it possible to apply in
是不是可以應用在
Can make full use of solar energy
可以充分利用太陽能
A visible dye has a wavelength of
可見的染料它的波長是
in the range of visible light
就是落在可見光的範圍
But the sun is actually very wide
但是太陽光事實上很寬
Depends on whether your material is made of organic materials or inorganic materials
要看你的材料是用有机的材料做还是无机的材料做
Inorganic materials are the solar panels we see on the market now
无机的材料就是我们现在看到市面上的太阳能的面板
Those are all composed of thin or inorganic elements
那个都是由细亚或者是无机的元素所构成的
The range of light absorption is very long
那个吸收光的范围就是很长
absorbs in the infrared range
就是在红外光的范围之内吸收
so yes indeed
所以是的确
We do research in the hope that
我们做研究事实上就是希望
Are we using organic materials?
我们是用有机的材料来做嘛
We just want to say that the range of organic materials that can absorb light
我们就希望说能够把有机材料吸收光的范围
stretch him out into the range of infrared light
把他拉宽拉到红外光的范围之内
But it's not easy to do it with organic materials
但是用有机的材料这样不是很容易做啦
Not as easy to make as inorganic materials
不像无机材料那么好做
Ok please finally because
好 请最后能因为
The four questions
那个四个问题请教
That is to say, the sun is yellowish in the morning
就是说那个太阳在早上是偏黄色
What was his eye shadow that was reddish that night
那个晚上偏红色他那个眼影是什么
The second one is the spectrum of sunlight and fluorescent lamps
那第二个就是说那个太阳光跟那个日光灯的光谱
is it the same
是不是相同
Isn't there a glass that allows the sunlight to pass through
不是有一種玻璃可以讓那個太陽光可以透過
But fluorescent lamps can't see through
但是日光燈沒辦法透過期這樣
Is there a way through this
有沒有辦法透過這樣
Then the Egyptian you just mentioned is
那你剛才提到那個埃及人是
The latest synthetic
最新的一個人工合成的
you want to hear that topic in england
你要聽到英國那個話題
again the first human
又是人類第一個
Synthetic pigments, these two
合成的色素那這兩個
where is the difference
差別是在哪裡
good
好
The last one is to say
最後一個就是說
black should be
黑色應該是
Easiest to absorb light
最容易吸收光
But in nature why
可是在自然界為什麼
Why is it developed that the nocturnal element is earth-colored to absorb light
為什麼是發展出來是夜曆素是地色的來吸收光
No development is black to absorb light
沒有發展是黑色的東西來吸收光
It's fun for me to answer your questions one by one
我一個一個來回答你問的問題很有趣
the first you say that
第一個你說那個
morning dusk
早晨黃昏
Why is the color of the sun's light different from the color of the light in the middle of the day?
的太陽光色為什麼跟日正當中的光色不太一樣
this fact
這個事實上
It has nothing to do with the material, it's all because
跟材料沒有關係那個完全是因為
So the light, the morning light or the yellow light
所以光線 早晨的光線或黃黃的光線
it shines on the surface of the earth
它照射到地球表面上
It has to penetrate the thicker atmosphere
它要穿透過比較厚的大氣層
The sun is directly above in the schedule
日程當中太陽就是在正上方
the depth of the atmosphere through which the earth passes
它照射到地球所經過的大氣層的深度
day and dusk, morning and dusk
跟白天黃昏 清晨跟黃昏
The thickness of the atmosphere it penetrates is different
它的穿透的大氣層的厚度是不一樣的
Are there many in the atmosphere?
那大氣層裡面是不是有很多
presence of floating particles
漂浮的微粒的存在
These floating particles and your light, light
這些漂浮的微粒跟你的光線 光線
The incoming light, the sun's rays will make some
入射的光線 太陽光線會起一些
phenomenon of diffraction or refraction
繞射或是折射的現象
This will make your light the sun's rays
這個會讓你的光 太陽光線的
Certain wavelengths of light are particularly intensified
某一些波長的光線特別加強
Some wavelengths of light are particularly weak
又有一些波長的光線會特別的變弱
so you would render
所以你會呈現出
Morning and evening light are different
早晨黃昏的光是不太一樣
this is
這個是
This is actually a physical optics reason
這個事實上是物理光學上的理由
I'm a chemistry student, in fact I'm not very
我是學化學事實上我並不是非常
But the first reason you just asked
但是您剛才問的第一個理由
Basically we interpret it this way
基本上我們是以這個方式來解釋
because it passes through the atmosphere at different thicknesses
因為它穿過大氣層的厚度不同
There are many floating particles in the atmosphere
大氣裡面有很多漂浮的微粒
this will diffract
這個會繞射
This existence is an optical phenomenon
這個存在是光學上的一個現象
will change the wavelength of some part of that sunlight
會改變那個太陽光的某部分的波長
Then the second question you asked is
那你問的第二個問題是說
Black
黑色的
no you asked
不是 你問的是
that glass is
那個玻璃就是
Glass sun rays can pass through
玻璃太陽光線可以傳透過去
Can the fluorescent lamp work?
那日光燈可不可以
No
沒有
you ask a question
你問一個問題是說
Is the light from a fluorescent tube the same as the sun's light?
日光燈管的光線跟太陽光線是不是
Is the spectrum
光譜是不是
is the same spectrum
是光譜相同
I say different
我說不一樣
is there a way to make a glass
有沒有辦法做一個玻璃
That is to say, the outside cannot see the inside
就是說讓外面看不到裡面
But you can see it from the outside
但是裡面看得到外面這種
just according to it
就根據它
pure glass no way
純粹的玻璃沒有辦法
but you can on the surface of the glass
但是你可以在玻璃的表面
Apply some material to achieve
塗抹一些材料可以達到
the purpose of this
這樣子的目的
For example, the most traditional way is to
譬如說最傳統的做法就是
you are like a mirror
你在就像鏡子一樣
You can add a reflective one inside
你可以在裡面加上一個反射的
translucent reflector
半透明的反射劑
You can't see the inside from the outside
外面就看不到裡面
But you can still see the outside
但是裡面還是可以看到外面
But when the website
可是在網站的時候
outside or see inside
外面還是看到裡面
I mean use them sunlight and daylight
我的意思說應用他們太陽光跟日光
The difference with the spectrum
跟光譜的差異
That is to say, let the sunlight pass through
就是說讓太陽光可以透過
Let the sunlight not see through
讓日光跟不能透出
As far as the website is concerned, sunlight cannot penetrate through it.
就網站日光跟不能透出去
Even if you throw it outside at night, you can't see inside.
那晚上丟外面也看不到裡面
this is a bit difficult
這個有點困難
because the solar spectrum
因為太陽光譜
basically covers all the rays
基本上是涵蓋了所有的光線
If you want to let the sun's rays
你如果要讓太陽光線
If everything penetrates the past
全部都穿透過去的話
should say so
應該這麼講
Fluorescent Tubes It Doesn't Cover All
日光燈管它並不是全部涵蓋了
All bands of sunlight
全部波段的太陽光線
So you can do a thing
所以你可以做一個東西
Limit light from fluorescent tubes
限制日光燈管的光線
Penetration does not penetrate
穿透不穿透
but you are hard
但是你很難
make a sun ray
做一個太陽光線
make a glass plate
做一片玻璃板子
Selectively let the sun's rays penetrate
選擇性的讓太陽光線穿透
impenetrable
不穿透
Because the solar spectrum is a relatively complete band
因為太陽光譜是比較完整的一個波段
On the contrary, it is easier to limit the light of fluorescent tubes
反而比較容易限制日光燈管的光線
because it's not all
因為它並不是全部
So you just put some fluorescent tubes
所以你只要把一些日光燈管
The material that absorbs fluorescent tubes
會吸收日光燈管的那個材料
sit in the glass
坐在玻璃裡面
In this way, the light of the fluorescent tube cannot penetrate
這樣的話日光燈管的光線就穿透不過去
But the sun is still
但是太陽光線還是可以
Because the sun's rays have a wider range of rays in its spectrum
因為太陽光線有涵蓋更廣的光線在它的光譜裡面
But it's not hard to do it the other way around
但是沒有很難反過來做
I just wish the sun could come in
我就是希望太陽光能夠進來
it was the time of fluorescent tubes
那是日光燈管的時候
It is so that at night, the outside cannot see the inside
就是讓晚上就是外面看不到裡面
Then why didn't this thing come out?
那為什麼這個東西沒有做出來
Because the spectrum of fluorescent tubes is relatively narrow
因為日光燈管的光譜比較窄
we are easier
我們比較容易
The narrow spectrum makes it impossible to get in and out
限制窄的光譜讓它沒辦法進出
But if it is wide, we must make it all to absorb the sun's rays
但是寬的我們就除非要全部做成吸收太陽光線
Then, of course, sunlight will be absorbed.
那的話日光當然也會被吸收
but you can make a tube that absorbs fluorescent light
但是你可以做出一個會吸收日光燈管
but some sun rays remain
但是還保留有一些太陽光線
not absorbed by it
沒有被它吸收的
do it the other way around
就反過來可以這麼做
But it's not easy to do it the other way around
但是要另外一個反過來做就不容易
It is easier for us to limit things with a narrower spectrum
我們比較容易去限制比較窄光譜的東西
But there is no way to limit the full spectrum of things
但是沒辦法去限制全光譜的東西
like this
是這樣子
Ig2 and that
Ig2跟那個
Both are actually the first inventions
兩個事實上都算是第一個發明的東西
But Ig's invention color uses different materials
但是Ig的發明顏色用的材料不一樣
Ig2 uses inorganic materials
Ig2用的是無機的材料
Purkin I also use organic materials
Purkin我也也是用的是有機材料
Inorganic materials are virtually unchanged in their composition
無機材料事實上它的組成並沒有被改變
It is derived from these fine acids, fine acid stones, malachite
它取材於這些細酸、細酸石、孔雀石
It is made up of atoms or ions of metals
它是由原子或是金屬的離子所構成的
it's just throwing it together and re-creating it
它只是把它擺在一起,把它重新做配方
Its composition has not been altered at all
它的組成完全沒有被改變
it just reformulates it
它只是把它重新做配方
Purkin-Wheel, different
Purkin-Wheel,不一樣
It is dismantling the original molecule
它是在把原來一個分子把它拆散開來
put it back together again
再把它重新組合回去
That's a chemical reaction
那是在做化學反應的
Although the Egyptians are also doing chemical reactions
雖然埃及的也是在做化學反應
The chemical reaction between the two is not the same
它這個兩者的化學反應不太一樣
One is organic synthesis and the other is inorganic synthesis
一個是有機合成,一個是無機合成
So if you speak in a broad sense, there is nothing wrong
所以你如果用廣義一點來講沒有錯
Egypt can also be said to be the first color to be artificially formulated.
埃及也算是說第一個用人工調配出來的顏色
Purkin-Wheel is equal to creating something from scratch
Purkin-Wheel等於是從無到有
Invent a new substance
全新發明一個新的物質出來
This is a place where the two are not the same
這是兩者不太一樣的一個地方
We also only call Pokéware the father of chemical engineering
我們也只把Pokéware稱之為叫做化工之父
because it lived in modern times
因為它比較活在近代
The Egyptians made that color at that time
埃及人那時候弄了那樣的顏色出來
But because it was too early
可是因為實在是太早之前了
There is no way to say that an industry will be produced.
那個也沒有辦法說產生一個工業出來
That era was a bit different
那個時代有點不太一樣
if the egyptian is later
如果那個埃及人是比較後面的話
Maybe at that time they will also send
說不定那時候他們也會發
At that time, an industrial-scale production of this scale will be developed.
那時候就會發展出工業級的這種規模產生
professor
教授
that is that black
那個是那個黑色
Black should be the most absorbing color
就是黑色應該是最會吸收顏色
Why Nature Is Green To Absorb That
為什麼自然界是綠色來吸收那個
Leaf green tree
葉綠樹
no
不是
Black means that several places have been absorbed
黑色是說好幾個地方都被吸收
absorbed it, right?
吸收掉了對不對
that's right
那果然沒有錯
If all the sun's rays are absorbed
太陽光線如果全部被吸收
just want it
就是要
All are absorbed everywhere
全部每個地方都被吸收
just rely on
就是要靠
by that black substance
靠那個黑色的物質
but you can see this nature
但是你可以看到這個自然界
except something is black
除了什麼東西是黑的之外
charcoal is black
木炭是黑的之外
Nothing seems black
好像沒有一個是黑的東西
The charcoal is not actually
那木炭事實上並不是
United speaking is not an organic substance
聯合講並不是有機物質
As far as we are concerned, there is life and there is no life
就我們講說有生命跟沒有生命
words to distinguish in the future
將來區分的話
so living things
所以有生命的東西
You'd be hard-pressed to find something all black one at a time
你很難很難找到一次一個全黑的東西
This if you really want to get to the bottom of it
這個如果你真的要追根究解的話
You may want to ask God about this
這個你可能要去問上帝吧
I do not want
我不想要
it the birth of this life of life
它這個生命的生命的產生
made of organic matter
就是由有機的物質所構成的
But organic matter is rarely seen and said to be completely black
但是有機物質很少很少看到說是全黑的
So I am more like this. Did you answer your question?
所以我比較有這樣子有沒有回答你的問題
That laver is purple
那個紫菜是紫色的
The pigment absorption of that seaweed
那個紫菜的那個色素吸收
Can wide and other abilities be entered into the wall at night?
廣等能力會不會被夜內入墻
you asked very well
你問得很好
That seaweed
那個紫菜啊
In fact it is because the color is very dark
事實上它是因為顏色很深
after you dilute the color
你把它顏色稀釋掉之後
it's not actually black
它事實上也不是黑色的
it's actually purple
它事實上是紫色的
Otherwise, it wouldn't be called laver.
不然的話不會叫紫菜吧
It's just because the color is very dark
它只是因為顏色非常深啊
But you go to analyze its color in fact
但是你去分析它的顏色事實上
it's not actually black
它事實上不是黑色
it's actually purple
它事實上是紫色
of a certain color
是某一種顏色的
OK, ask the professor
OK的請問教授
Just now we talked about asking the professor
剛剛我們有談到那個請教教授
Use of Exciting Phosphors and Non-Exciting Phosphors
有激發光體與無激發光體的用途
where is the biggest difference
最大的差別在哪裡
There are also pros and cons of both
還有兩者的優缺點
Thanks
謝謝
good
好
because of time
因為時間的關係
We're going to get it down to that detail
我們要把它講到那麼的細了
you ask me questions
你問我的問題
In fact, it is my research
事實上就是我的研究的
where the expertise is doing
專長在做的地方
Its priorities actually have their own priorities. Let me first say that what I am best at is organic light-emitting diodes.
它的優先點事實上各有優先點,我先講我最擅長的就是有機的發光二級體,
The two things lead to a very different manufacturing process. The manufacturing process of organic light-emitting diodes is not like that of inorganic light-emitting diodes.
這個兩者的東西牽的到那個製程很不一樣,有機發光二級體的製程不像無機發光二級體的製程,
There will be no high-temperature processing stage, because the materials are different,
不會遇到高溫的處理的階段,因為材料不一樣,
It makes all very thin films, and the inorganic must use high heat to perform the fusion action.
它製作通通都是很薄的膜,無機必須要用高熱的方式去做融合的動作,
Because the material is different, organic actually does not need high temperature, it uses a little temperature, about 100 degrees C is enough,
因為材質不一樣,有機事實上它不需要高溫,它是用一點點的溫度,大概就100度C就可以了,
In fact, inorganic materials need to use 300 or 400 degrees C to make thin films. This is because the manufacturing process is different.
無機事實上要用到300、400度C才能夠做出薄膜的形式,這個是製程不一樣,
The difference in the manufacturing process will lead to the difference in the equipment you use when making it.
製程不一樣就牽的到你製作的時候所用到的儀器設備就很不一樣,
Using high heat to make films, the equipment is very expensive
用高熱的做薄膜 那個機器設備非常的昂貴
consumes energy
又耗費能源
Organic does not require high heat
用有機的不需要高溫高熱
So its equipment is different
所以它那個機器設備就不一樣嘛
Again, because it is not used for high temperature and high heat
再來就是說 因為它不是用在高溫高熱上
so it can sit on this soft board
所以它可以坐在這種軟性的機板上面
Because generally we talk about soft plastic sheets
因為一般我們講軟性的就是塑膠片子
You can bend when you sit on a soft surface
坐在軟性的上就可以彎曲啦
Bending Now Everyone's Talking
彎曲現在大家都在講說
The scoopable panel is an attractive application
可撈式的面板 這個是很吸引的那個應用
Inorganic materials because of the need to use high heat
無機的材料因為需要用到高熱的關係
so it can't sit on a soft board
所以它不可能坐在軟性的機板上
So what about this inorganic LED?
所以這個無機的LED呢
It can't be made into a curved or fishable display
它沒有辦法做成一個彎曲式或者可撈式的顯示器
no way
沒有辦法
Because if you want to be fishable, you must sit on a hard board
因為你要可撈式一定要坐在一個硬的機板上
It is due to high heat
它因為用高熱的關係
no way to sit on the plastic sheet
就沒辦法坐在塑膠片子上
The plastic sheet just melts, so there's no way to do that.
塑膠片子就融化掉了 就沒辦法這麼做
Then there's both because that
那還有兩者的 因為那個
It's a lot of telecommunications
它的電信上的超多
In fact, there is something different
其實又有一點不太一樣
So it actually varies in efficiency
所以它的效率上事實上會有所差別
And if you talk about the lighting
還有就是如果你再說一下照明方面
There will be some difference in brightness
亮度上也會有一些差別
In terms of efficiency and brightness
那個效率跟亮度就這方面來講
Or is it actually better to be inorganic?
還是事實上是無機的比較好
Organic is worse
有機的比較差
So each has pros and cons
所以各有優缺點
Also, organic materials are cheaper to make
還有就是有機的材料製作比較便宜
inorganic material
無機的材料
I will use some expensive and rare metals for the net
網我會用到一些比較昂貴稀有的金屬
that will be more expensive
那個會比較昂貴
So in terms of cost
所以就成本上面而言
Organic materials are so-called OLEDs
有機的材料就是所謂的OLED
cost is cheaper
成本是比較便宜的
But this is entangled again
但是這個又糾纏在一起
That is to say but its organic OLED
就是說但是它的有機OLED
Its efficiency and brightness are relatively poor
它的效率跟亮度又比較差
So in order to make up for this efficiency and brightness
所以為了彌補這個效率跟亮度
you do more
你要做更多
So it's cheap but not really cheap
所以它的成本便宜也不見得真正便宜到哪裡去
This is where many issues are entangled together.
這個是就很多問題都糾纏在一起了
But basically they have their own strengths
但是基本上是各有所長
right
對
How does this matter in simple terms
這個事到簡單來講是怎樣
There are many things involved
是中間還牽扯很多事情
good
好
later
後面
Professor I want to ask a simple question
教授我想問一個簡單的問題
Is this kind of light-emitting secondary body harmful to health?
就是這種發光二級體對於健康有沒有影響
Because I see that mobile phones are becoming more and more common now
因為我看到現在手機越來越普遍
Small-sized big-sized TVs keep getting bigger
小尺寸的大尺寸的電視越來越大
colorful
色彩繽紛
But my thought is whether it is harmful to our health
但是我的想法是對我們的健康是不是有傷害
then if there is harm
那麼如果有傷害
how much it hurts
它會傷害到什麼程度
This question has been raised by many people
這個問題有很多人提出來過了
In fact it's
其實它的
because it
因為它
Basically the light it emits
基本上它所發出來的光線
It is very similar to the traditional light
就跟傳統的光線很類似了
If you want to explore carefully, say
如果你要去仔細的去探討說
That
那
what kind of light
什麼樣的光線
that is
就是
it
它
Is light harmful to the human body more or less
光線對人體傷害比較大還是小
This is not easy to define clearly
這個不是很容易界定的清楚
Generally we talk
一般我們講說
Ultraviolet light can be harmful to our body
紫外光會對我們人體傷害比較大
But the traditional glowing things
但是傳統的這些發光的東西
It actually has a lot of UV light too
它事實上也有很多紫外光
that for example
那譬如
As for these relatively modern LED light bulbs
那至於像這個比較近代的這些LED的燈泡
or that energy saving light bulb
或是那個省電燈泡
Its ultraviolet light content is also no more than
它的紫外光線的含量也沒有比
Generally, where do the light bulbs come from?
一般那個燈泡來得多到哪裡去
Because the light diagrams of the two are actually a bit different
因為兩者的光圖事實上有點不太一樣
so its ultraviolet part
所以它的紫外光的部分
In fact, there is indeed a difference
事實上是的確是有多寡的差異
But the difference between the two
但是那個兩者的差異
i don't know
我不曉得
To what extent is it harmful to human health?
對人體的健康的危害有大到什麼樣的程度
Of course, if you look like this in any January of this year
當然你如果今年哪一月這樣子
under the sun
曝曬之下
Of course that effect I will often
當然那個效果我會常常
will show up
就會顯現出來了
On the contrary, on the contrary, what I will say later is to say
反而 反而 另外我後來講就是說
Current lighting fixtures
現在的照明的燈具
Much brighter than traditional lighting fixtures
比起傳統的照明燈具都亮很多
On the contrary, the damage of this is greater than the amount of ultraviolet light.
反而這個的傷害還比說紫外光多少來得大
Because too much light always hurts the eyes
因為光線太強總是會傷害眼睛
So now a lot of lighting is changed to LED lighting
所以現在很多照明都改成用LED裝照明
That light is very bright, isn't it?
那個光線非常的亮對不對
will be bright enough to dazzle
會亮到刺眼的一個程度
traditional lamps
傳統的燈具
because it's not that bright
因為它沒有那麼的亮
So its damage to the eyes is actually relatively slight
所以它對眼睛的傷害事實上是比較輕微的
If you look at the intensity of the light
如果你就光線的強弱而言
there would be a worrying place like this
會有這樣子的一個令人擔心的地方
It takes a long time to be exposed like this
這個都是要很長時間這樣子照射之下
to show this symptom
才會顯現出這個症狀
Is it the so-called light pollution?
就是所謂的那個光害嘛
light pollution
光害 對
It's too bright, just don't look at it if it's too bright
太亮了 就是太亮就不要去看
Why is there so much light on this point
這一點為什麼那麼多 light
ok, is there any problem
OK,還有沒有什麼問題
OK
OK
How to solve the toxicity of dye
染料的毒性怎麼解決
dye toxicity
染料的毒性
you say this these dyes
你說這個這些染料
In fact, it's more or less toxic.
事實上多多少都是有些毒性的
How to deal with it
怎麼解決
Just like the general dye toxicity solution
就跟一般的染料的毒性的解決方法一樣
Meltase
Meltase
let red settle
讓紅色解決
What method do we use for general dyes
一般的染料我們是用什麼方法
to analyze to quantify
來分析來做定量
that is an analytical tool
那個是分析方面的工具
to do quantitative testing
去做定量的檢測
For example, what happened to them a while ago?
譬如說他們那個前陣子什麼
Didn't the industry peer ratio have to be analyzed?
同業率數那不是有去做分析說
How much is there in it?
這裡面含量有多少嗎
is the same method
就是同樣的一個方法
is using the same method
是用同樣一個方法
Food testing for those various ingredients
食品檢驗那些各式各樣的成分
Some of it is used, Zhi Puyi is doing the inspection
它有的是用就是植樸儀在做檢查
Some are for actual quantitative analysis
有的是去做實際的定量的分析出來
go to assess say
去評估說
Inside content of multiple tubes
裡面的含量的多管
the technique is the same
那個技術是都一樣的
There is no need to rely on any special method
並沒有需要靠什麼特殊的方式
good
好
Why does some of the fuel recede and some
那個燃料為什麼有一些會退水有一些
oh
喔
That one is destroyed by chemicals
那個因為化學物質被破壞了
Organic matter is easily explained as
有機的物質很容易解釋就是
I also said at the beginning
我們一開始我也講說
The shape of that color is because of its
那個顏色的成型都是因為它那個
many double bonds
很多個雙鍵
Carbon-carbon double bonds accumulate together
碳碳雙鍵累積在一起
After the light shines for a long time
那光線照久了之後
Or after it shines for a long time
或者是它發光發久了之後
Some of that double bond will be destroyed
那個雙鍵有的會被破壞掉
After the double bond is broken
那個雙鍵破壞掉之後
after its number dwindles
它的數目變少之後
its color will disappear completely
它的顏色就會滿消失掉
That inorganic material is another way of explaining
那無機材料是另外一個解釋的方式
is its color
就是它的造成顏色
is in fact related to its constituent elements
是事實上是跟它的構成的元素的
Oxidation state is related
氧化態有關係
after a long time
時間久了之後
Those oxidation states will be oxidized by air
那個那些氧化態會被空氣給氧化
right
對
Once its oxidation state is changed
它的氧化態一旦被改變的時候
Its color will also be changed
它的顏色也會被改變
that often just disappears
那往往就是會變成消失
This is to see whether it is human pigment dye
這就是看到不管只要是人座的色素染料
There will be this problem of getting this fading
都會有牽得到這個褪色的這個問題
It's just a matter of time
只是時間長短的問題啦
ok one last question this way in the middle
好 最後一個問題請這邊中間
So, how do you tell the difference between the fluorescent light and the aura?
那個請問一下那個螢光跟靈光怎麼分呢
I could spend an hour explaining to you
我可以花一個小時的時間來跟你解釋
This leads to the basic phenomenon of photophysics.
這個牽得到基本的光物理的現象啦
yes in short
有好 簡而言之啦
The length of life of their light is not the same
他們發光的壽命時間長短是不一樣的
Theoretically, they are produced from different states
學理上面他們是從不同的狀態下產生的
So if you're going to say what can we do
所以如果你要去說我們有什麼辦法
eyes can't tell the difference
眼睛是區分不出來
Because of the difference in the speed of his time
因為他的時間的快慢的差距
beyond the limits of human vision
都超過人的眼睛的視覺的極限
we can't tell the difference
我們區分不出來
Which is faster or slower needs to be distinguished by instruments
那個快慢那個需要靠儀器來做區分
There is also their fluorescent light and aura of the same substance
還有就是他們的同一個物質的螢光跟靈光
its wavelength is different
它的波長是不一樣的
Usually the aura is longer and the fluorescence is shorter
通常靈光比較長 螢光比較短
That also requires you to rely on instruments and equipment to control
那個也是要你要靠儀器設備去把
Simultaneously two lights are recorded
同時兩個光記錄下來
You know that the one with the long wavelength is the aura
你就知道說長波長的那個就是靈光
The short wavelength is fluorescence
短波長的那個就是螢光
It can be divided from these two ways
可以從這個兩個方式來做去分
Sorry to ask Professor Lin again
不好意思 再次請教林教授
So about the Liao legacy lamp we talked about just now
所以有關剛剛我們談到那個遼遺燈
That is to say, too strong will affect the eyes
就是說太強烈會影響眼睛
To make the lights in our house the best is to say
讓我們家裡的燈最好就是說
Use about how much brightness like this
用差不多多少亮度這樣
For the upper half of the eyes and then bright enough thank you
為上半眼睛然後又夠亮 謝謝
it's very important
這是切身問題很重要
I'm not very clear about this
這個我不是很清楚
You might ask your doctor for a better understanding
你可能要去問醫生會比較了解
Because we need different brightness for different occasions
因為不同的場合我們有需要不同亮度
Right, for example, our weaknesses don't need to be very bright
對不對 譬如說我們的弱勢不需要很亮
because it's time to sleep
因為要睡覺了
but the office
但是辦公的地方
because we want to see something
因為我們要看東西
be bright with me
都要跟我很亮
But the human eye has a limit
但是人的眼睛的都有個極限
Ask the ophthalmologist about the limit
那個極限要問眼科醫生
may be clearer
可能會比較清楚
makes sense thank you
有道理 謝謝
OK
OK
Our K-A mates really thank you
我們K-A的同伴們真的謝謝
then our first thank you
那我們第一次謝謝
This wonderful interview with Dr. Chen
這個陳博士的這個精采的採訪
thank you all
謝謝大家